<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep Learning | Jim Coll</title>
    <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/tags/deep-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jimcoll.github.io/tags/deep-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Deep Learning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Internal Project</title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/YUN00120.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;drones-for-mapping-and-research&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drones for mapping and research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many reasons I gravitated towards the Environmental Sciences, but perhaps the single largest factor was the practicality of the problem.  While we could devise any number of conceptual models for the world while in the lab, at the end of the day if we wanted to know how things worked in the “real” world all we had to do was go outside and observe.  However, as both my understanding of the world and our technical abilities increased, I became increasingly interested in how to best represent earth system processes, and our uncertainties in them, within a digital environment.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/KS_Lawrence West_511813_1950_24000_tn.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When most think of how we represent landforms, there are two basic formats with which they conjure.  You might recall old USGS contour maps, showing the terrain and prominent land cover features.  If you’re more technically oriented, you might imagine a view of the world though Google Earth Engine.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/GISData.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These representations are perfect for conveying the basic geographic context of an area, but if you want to go further than that, we have to turn towards a more advanced means of representing reality.  Enter the world of airborne observations.  Lidar surveys are the newest state of the art means of collecting large areas of high-resolution elevation data.  More commonly known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usgs.gov/core-science-systems/ngp/3dep&#34;&gt;3DEP&lt;/a&gt;, this effort seeks to provide complete and high accuracy coverage across CONUS (Contiguous United States).  This used to be the state of the art, and should be completed by 2023
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/FY19_Partnerships_territories_08212019.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
As is usually the case though, it’s never good enough.  Depending on the location and use case, imagery is hard to come by or outdated for the use case.  In these instances, small Unmanned Aerial Systems, more commonly known as drones, offer a unique solution to some of these shortcomings.  Using commercially available hardware and cutting edge software, we are able to fly over an area and collect imagery which we use to create our own custom point clouds and 3D models.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/OreadOrthoTrimmedSmaller.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/YUN00016.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
As a critical part of my dissertation, I am interested in flying areas to determine what factors go into an effective terrestrial mapping effort.  If you have an area you would like flown, particularly if it has interesting and complex geometry or if it’s near a body of water, please contact me and we can see what we can work out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
