<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jim Coll</title>
    <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jim Coll</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://jimcoll.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Jim Coll</title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/classoutline/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/classoutline/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This is a living document.  Changes will be announced in class.  The main course page syllabus supersedes this one in all cases.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-description&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Description:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the introductory GIS class, this course focuses primarily on teaching advanced spatial analysis methods with applications in the mapping of surface water and the analysis of water related environmental issues. Major topics covered include map algebra (also called cartographic modeling), multi-criteria evaluation, terrain analysis, spatial statistics, and spatial interpolation. An additional objective of the course is to have students become familiar with various methods and tools through the use of GIS software.  Continuing with the industry standard GIS software, this class expands on GIS platforms through the use of the ArcGIS software suite. Finally, this class counts towards the &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalog.ku.edu/liberal-arts-sciences/geography/geographic-information-science-ucert/&#34;&gt;certificate in GIS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;student-responsibilities&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Responsibilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is student’s responsibility to attend the lectures, do the readings, and finish lab assignments. All students should be prepared to participate in class discussion and answer questions when called upon.  All students are expected to complete labs and exams on time. Labs are due at the beginning of the lab period one week after they are assigned, unless otherwise noted. Detailed lab rules will be given by the teaching assistant in the first lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;expectations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expectations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attend every Class/lab and &lt;strong&gt;ask questions!&lt;/strong&gt; At times, the ArcGIS software can be very unforgiving, and GIS can seem like a foreign language. The last thing I want is for you to walk out of this class without understanding the material. I expect and hope that this will be a rewarding experience for everyone. We are available to answer questions and otherwise offer assistance during the office hours indicated above or by appointment.  Additionally, if you have any questions, feel free to drop me an e-mail or use the slack channel (The link will be passed around on the sign up sheet at the beginning of the year). I try to be diligent about responding to emails and by using slack you are likely to get a very rapid response&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computers in the lab are not cheap to replace. Please do your part to lengthen their lives by not spilling coffee/soda/liquids of any kind on the computer or any of its parts. You do NOT need to go out and purchase a computer for this class, although I do recommend having a personal computer with ArcGIS installed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computer recommendations:  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ArcGIS is a demanding program, and a lower grade computer is not recommended.  If you are at KU, IT offers &lt;a href=&#34;https://kuit.service-now.com/kb_view.do?sysparm_article=KB0011590&#34;&gt;virtualLabs&lt;/a&gt;, a remote desktop program you can use to access ArcMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to purchase a computer, I offer these general guidelines. You should aim for a 64-bit computer (x64), and aside from that I like to prioritize CPU &amp;amp; RAM &amp;gt; video &amp;amp; hard drive speed &amp;gt; hard drive space (External hard drives are really cheap, and as long as the computer has a USB port you are good to go).  For the last few years I&amp;rsquo;ve deferred to the pre-built pc choices on &lt;a href=&#34;https://buildmypc.net/&#34;&gt;https://buildmypc.net/&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://pcpartpicker.com/&#34;&gt;https://pcpartpicker.com/&lt;/a&gt;.
In general, I tend to stay away from the &amp;ldquo;gaming&amp;rdquo; laptops.  For those prices, you can build a much more powerful desktop and get a lot more mileage out of it, but that&amp;rsquo;s just me.  If you want to go that route however virtually all will meet your school related needs.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pcpartpicker.com/user/JColl/saved/#view=zddq3C&#34;&gt;My “Ideal” build (This is excessive, visualization grade)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lab is open for students whenever there is no scheduled class (see the calendar posted on the lab door. Additionally, ArcMap is available in the GIS lab on the second floor of Watson Library, and on the Architecture and Engineering computers if you have access to those. A signup sheet will also be passed around at the beginning of the semester for those who wish to install ArcGIS on your own personal computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-integrity&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academic Integrity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, cheating and/or plagiarism &lt;strong&gt;is not tolerated&lt;/strong&gt;. Feel free to discuss the labs with your classmates, but all work you turn in should be your own, and it&amp;rsquo;s insert year here, how hard is it to give someone credit for their work?  I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; for my citation needs, as a KU student you have access to Endnote through &lt;a href=&#34;https://technology.ku.edu/software/microsoft-office&#34;&gt;Office 365&lt;/a&gt;, and in a pinch &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.citethisforme.com/us/citation-generator&#34;&gt;Cite This for Me&lt;/a&gt; will also work for you in a pinch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disabilities&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disabilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has a disability that may prevent full demonstration of academic ability should contact me as soon as possible to ensure accommodations can be made to allow for full educational benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-labs&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the Labs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a cartography course; however, the final product of the majority of the labs is a map (or maps) of some sort. The grade you receive on the maps will be based primarily on the results of the relevant analysis, not cartographic technique (there is a whole class dedicated to this; GEOG 211). That said, some level of cartographic knowledge will be useful to effectively communicate with maps, and will be stressed in critiques of your submissions. As the semester wears on we expect improvements and may begin taking points off for excessively bad cartographic technique. Please refer to the cartography resources linked below for some basic guidelines or ask for feedback.  In addition, each lab will specify the steps to follow with regards to what to submit for grading and how to do so. Please don’t make assumptions. Follow these instructions carefully; failure to submit the correct files or submission of files in an incorrect fashion will result in drastic loss of points. Don’t turn a potential A into an F due to failure to follow directions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cartography-primers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cartography primers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&#34;&gt;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&#34;&gt;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://colorbrewer2.org/#type=sequential&amp;amp;scheme=BuGn&amp;amp;n=3&#34;&gt;http://colorbrewer2.org/#type=sequential&amp;amp;scheme=BuGn&amp;amp;n=3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;textbooks&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbooks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;de Smith, M. J., M. F. Goodchild, P. A. Longley (2018) Geospatial Analysis—A
comprehensive guide (6th edition), An online version is available at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&#34;&gt;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-evaluation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Evaluation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course grade will be evaluated based on two exams, ten lab exercises, and a final project.
The exams will include materials from the textbooks, lecture slides, handouts, and labs. Mid-term
exam will cover the materials from the first half of the class, and the final exam will focus on the
second half. The final exam is not comprehensive, but since we will be building on concepts
throughout the semester, materials from the first half of the semester will inevitably be part of the
final exam. A breakdown of grade weights is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Midterm exam 20%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final exam 20%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labs 40%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final Project 20%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade will be on a straight scale, not on a curve. If you all do well, you will all get
an A. Letter grades will be determined based on the standard grading scale. Each student will
complete a final project. The project will be presented to the class during the last two weeks of
class. Details on the final project can be found in the final project handout. Letter grades will be
determined based on the following grading scale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;F&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;100 - 97&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;96 - 93&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;92 - 90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;89 - 87&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;86 - 83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;82 - 80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;79 - 77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;76 - 73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;72 - 70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;69 - 67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;66 - 63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;62 - 60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exams&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mid-term exam will cover the materials from the first half of the class, and the final exam will focus on the second half. The final exam is not comprehensive, but since we will be building on concepts throughout the semester, materials from the first half of the semester will inevitably be part of the final exam.  &lt;del&gt;Either exam may include a practical portion.  This practical portion will consist of instructions to prepare some sort of short analysis or demonstration of practical knowledge related to the use of ArcGIS.  These will be posted either a week before the exam and due on the date of the exam, or posted the day of the exam and due a week after.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab01/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    These labs are largely written for ArcMap 10.6.  However, operations from ArcMap 10.2 through 10.6 and even up to Pro all largely look the same although some of the tools may have shifted or changed names just to keep you on your toes.  Although these labs are written so that you can follow them step by step, I expect you to flex those critical thinking skills of yours.  Take a step back, read the learning objectives and ask yourself what steps are needed to get to that goal.  When in doubt, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lmgtfy.com/&#34;&gt;Google it&lt;/a&gt;!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-1-a-survey-of-data-and-mapping-technologies-and-database-building&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 1: A survey of data and mapping technologies and database building&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of this lab requires writing a survey of the data and mapping technologies in the field that you are interested in (wildlife reserve, conservation, urban planning, forest resources, natural hazards, business, etc.), not limited to the data and mapping technologies covered in the lecture. This survey may include both traditional and new emerging datasets and/or mapping technologies that are used in the fields. The second part of the lab will download imagery and create a database that will be used for the next few labs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit the paper outlined in part 1, and the screenshot of the data you downloaded in part 2 to blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-70-points-a-survey-of-data-and-mapping-technologies&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1 (70 points): A survey of data and mapping technologies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will write a survey on the data and mapping technologies in a field that you are interested in. The survey should have 2-4 single spaced pages using a font size of 12 points. Reference style should follow one of the GIS journal reference styles (e.g. Transactions in GIS, Cartography and Geographic Information Science, International Journal of Geographic Information Science, The Geographical Journal, and Computers &amp;amp; Geosciences, etc.). I also point you to several resources for reference management software &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/classoutline/#academic-integrity&#34;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grading for the survey is based on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(80%) Quality of the content: how many potential datasets and mapping methods are included; How you organize your contents. Whether the length of survey is proper, and has a proper level of synthesis and details.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(20%) Format: follow the requirements described above and check your grammar, spelling and sentence structures before you submit the survey.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-30-points-building-a-database&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2 (30 points): Building a database&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our goals over the the next couple of labs is to recreate part of the analysis found in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/feart.2018.00210/full&#34;&gt;Frey et al., 2018&lt;/a&gt;, specifically Figure 2 and a lake volume estimation.  We will use these data in the next couple of labs and I will not wait for you to download them next week so be prepared to have them ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-folders-and-accounts&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting up folders and accounts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some sort of file management system is preferable to nothing.  Time wasted looking for files can be better spent performing the analysis, other research, or discovering new music.  Below I will outline what I use, but if you already have a system that works for you feel free to deviate.  Just as an aside, avoid file names with spaces, leading numbers, or strange characters.
&lt;li&gt;On OneDrive, create a folder for classes, in that one for this class (GEOG558), and in that folder create one for labs.  In that folder create one for Lab01, and one for base data (BaseData).  In that create folders, one called Elevation and the other called Landsat.  The Landsat tiles can get a little messy so I create extra folders underneath the Landsat folder titled something along the lines of LS05_YYYY.  
&lt;li&gt;We will use USGS Earth Explorer to download the requisite datasets, including Landsat scenes and elevation data.  Before we start you&#39;ll need accounts at both &lt;a href=&#34;https://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/&#34;&gt;https://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://urs.earthdata.nasa.gov/&#34;&gt;https://urs.earthdata.nasa.gov/&lt;/a&gt;  
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;downloading-data&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downloading data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up &lt;a href=&#34;https://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/&#34;&gt;Earthexplorer&lt;/a&gt;  
&lt;li&gt;We first need to define our area of interest.  Under the Search Criteria tab change the coordinate box to decimal degrees, add a coordinate, and copy/paste the following into their respective fields.  
&lt;/ol&gt;  
  

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latitude: -9.397055203542507&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longitude: -77.38027425750124&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the Data Sets tab, search for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/products/srtmgl1v003&#34;&gt;SRTM3 SRTMGL-1&lt;/a&gt; and make sure the box next to the dataset is checked.  Click results and then download the standard format (the HGT, not any of the metadata).  
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few useful buttons on a results screen.  The black footprint shows you the footprint of a tile, and the image icon will draw a jpg over the browser so you can see what the data you&amp;rsquo;re downloading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elevation data is distributed as a nested zip file.  To use it you&#39;ll need to unzip it twice to actually use it in a program.  Unzip (Right click &gt; 7-Zip &gt; Extract to “FileNameHere”) the SRTMGL folder and move the HGT file (a fancy tif for SRTM data) intoyour folder structure.  
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we want the Landsat scenes.  We&amp;rsquo;ll simplify this somewhat by starting at 1995 and looking forward in time every 2 year.  We&amp;rsquo;ll also use scenes taken in the winter, so that the lake is stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the Data Sets tab, navigate to the Landsat &amp;gt; Landsat Collection 1 Level 1 check &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usgs.gov/centers/eros/science/usgs-eros-archive-landsat-archives-landsat-4-5-thematic-mapper-tm-level-1-data?qt-science_center_objects=0#qt-science_center_objects&#34;&gt;Landsat 4-5 TM C1 Level-1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the Date Range dates to 06/01/1995 and 08/01/1995 respectively.
&lt;li&gt;Click on Additional Criteria, set the Land Cloud Cover to less than 10%&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on Results, when the images load in you can explore them with the “Show Browser Overlay” button, and download the desired tiles (Get the Level-1 GeoTIFF data products.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do this for every two years up to 2009 (change the Date Range on the Search Criteria tab).  The images I selected for this analysis were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;YEAR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;SCENE NAME&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008067_19950622_20170109_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1997&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008066_19970729_20161230_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1999&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008067_19990601_20161217_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008067_20010622_20161210_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008066_20030714_20161205_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008066_20050703_20161126_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008067_20070725_20161112_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LT05_L1TP_008066_20090628_20161024_01_T1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Landsat tiles are downloaded with extensions .tar.gz, they’ve also essentially been compressed twice.  Unzip them the first time, open them up and unzip them a second time.  Copy all the files into their respective folders.
&lt;li&gt;Open up ArcMap and the ArcCatalog window, connect to the lab folder, and expand the BaseData file tree out a bit.  Submit a screenshot of your final files (similar to the one below).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab1Image2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab02/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Labs in the intermediate class are a fair bit more involved than their intro to GIS counterparts.  Judicious use of the table of contents to the right to navigate will save your scroll wheel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-2-cartographic-modeling&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 2 - Cartographic Modeling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lab will introduce local operations using cartographic modeling (map algebra).  Part 1 is intended to show you how you can organize and display raster datasets in a usable format.  Part 2 will walk you through how to calculate NDWI and perform a water area analysis.  Part 3 you will model the geographic distribution of Kudzu in the conterminous United States and then compare your model to the actual geographic distribution, using Map Algebra and attribute table manipulation.  I&amp;rsquo;ve prefaced each lab with the learning objectives of the exercise, what you need to submit to blackboard, a set of materials for the lab as appropriate, and then the instructions for the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint: Copy and paste the questions below into a word document and submit it to blackboard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 2: Answer Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Name:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Lake delineation and water classification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Based on the results from 1995, which water delineation metric would you choose to perform this analysis, NDWI or MNDWI.  Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 2&lt;/strong&gt;: What is the area of the lake in 1995?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Calculate the area of the lake for 2003 and 2009.  Finish the table below and create a short graph of the area through time.  Create a short map of the before/after.
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Year  # of Pixels&lt;br /&gt;
1995:  xxx&lt;br /&gt;
1997:  100&lt;br /&gt;
1999:  143&lt;br /&gt;
2001:  184&lt;br /&gt;
2003:  xxx&lt;br /&gt;
2005:  437&lt;br /&gt;
2007:  503&lt;br /&gt;
2009:  xxx  &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab2AnswerSheet1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Composite images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question 4&lt;/strong&gt;: Create another graph as was performed above&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 5&lt;/strong&gt;: What are some potential issues of using gap-filled imagery for scientific analysis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Kudzu Suitability Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question 6&lt;/strong&gt;: The minimum annual precipitation for Kudzu to survive is:________&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question 7&lt;/strong&gt;: The minimum frost free day for Kudzu to survive is:________&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question 8&lt;/strong&gt;: The total area (in m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) suitable for Kudzu to survive (according to your model) is:________  (m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 9&lt;/strong&gt;: Complete the following table:
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}
.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-lqy6{text-align:right;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-dvpl{border-color:inherit;text-align:right;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34; colspan=&#34;2&#34; rowspan=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-c3ow&#34; colspan=&#34;2&#34;&gt;Actual Kudzu Distribution&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-c3ow&#34;&gt;No Kudzu&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-baqh&#34;&gt;Kudzu&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-c3ow&#34; rowspan=&#34;2&#34;&gt;Your Model&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-c3ow&#34;&gt;No Kudzu&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;D:(00)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-lqy6&#34;&gt;B:(10)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-c3ow&#34;&gt;Kudzu&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;C:(01)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-lqy6&#34;&gt;A:(11)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assess the accuracy of your model by filling in the following information.  For more about confusion matrices look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confusion_matrix&#34;&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accuracy - ((A+D)/(A+B+C+D)):&lt;br /&gt;
False Positive Rate - (C/(A+C)):&lt;br /&gt;
False Omission Rate - (B/(A+B)):&lt;br /&gt;
MCC - (A*D-B*C)/sqrt((A+B)*(A+C)*(D+B)*(D+C)):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 10&lt;/strong&gt;: Discuss some of the reasons for the inaccuracy of your model. In particular, examine why the error may be occurring. Also, looking at your kudzu_model layer, where geographically do you think this error is?  (Hint: Consider the factors that your model did not include that could explain the geography of the model’s error)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kansas-my.sharepoint.com/:f:/g/personal/j610c377_home_ku_edu/EuPaly9t2yxGrCruD_fcGakBSzTfsGwq5KC-iWYwU6GNog?e=YznxCc&#34;&gt;click to download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Relevant part&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;BaseData&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Data we downloaded as part of lab 1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;usanpre25k&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;annual precipitation in mm (25000m grid)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;usfrost25k&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;number of frost-free-days in conterminous US (25000m grid)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;sample1.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;point file showing locations of known presence/absence of Kudzu (to be used to make model)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;sample2.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;point file showing locations of known presence/absence of Kudzu (to be used for accuracy assessment)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you are short on space, you only need the .mpk from part 2, the LANDSAT tiles are ~20 gigs and are provided for reproducibilities sake.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-lake-delineation-and-water-classification&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Lake delineation and water classification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-the-mxd&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting up the MXD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up a new ArcMap document.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, a few housekeeping items.  Let’s take the training wheels off ArcMap and make sure we can overwrite data.  Click Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Geoprocessing Options and make sure the top two boxes in this window are selected.  You may also want to increase the time period results are stored to a month or so.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the 1995 year, add in the green, NIR, MIR, and MTL bands/images.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint#1: When performing the NDWI calculation, we refer to bands based their wavelength (e.g. green, NIR).  However, when distributing data the bands are referred to by their number based on sensor properties (so in our case, LANDSAT 5 TM has 7 bands and change).  GEE provides a nice, concice overview of a remote sensing products bands, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/LANDSAT_LT05_C01_T1&#34;&gt;https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/LANDSAT_LT05_C01_T1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
Hint#2: A note about pyramids:  You will want to build pyramids when you add raster images into ArcMap.  You will notice that when this is done, ArcMap will create a file with a .ovr extension (look using the Windows file browser).  We&amp;rsquo;ll talk about pyramids in class more, but as a cursory introduction, think about Google Maps.  When you zoom out to look at the entire planet, there is no physical way to represent 30 meters on the screen.  Instead, we take a generalization of all the pixels underneath the region and display those values in their place.  Because Google sets the standards for mapping, there are generally 21 levels of images that are loaded in, with the top most layer being zoom level 1, and increasing as you zoom in.  See an interactive example of this concept in action at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maptiler.com/google-maps-coordinates-tile-bounds-projection/&#34;&gt;https://www.maptiler.com/google-maps-coordinates-tile-bounds-projection/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02Picture01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select all 4 images using shift-click, and right click &amp;gt; Group to place them in a group.  Slow click and rename this group to LS1995&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02Picture02.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, let&amp;rsquo;s find our lake using the go to xy tool and copy/pasting the lat/long in: -9.3970552,-77.3802742
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-an-area-of-interest-aoi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating An Area of Interest (AOI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Skill review from &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog358/lab04/#part-2-on-screen-digitizing&#34;&gt;Lab 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We next need to create a shape representing the area of analysis.  First, right click on your BaseData folder and create a new File Geodatabase.  Rename the database to &lt;em&gt;LakePalcacocha.gdb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on the new geodatabase and go to New &amp;gt; Feature Class&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Name the Feature Class AOI and set the type to polygon.  Click next.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scroll to the bottom of the window, expand the Layers folder, and click on the only option (WGS_1984_UTM_Zone_18N | WKID: 32618).  Click through the rest of the setup dialog to finish creating the shapefile.  Assuming you were successful you should now have a new layer called AOI in your TOC&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start an editing session (Editor toolbar &amp;gt; Editor &amp;gt; Start editing)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you are editing the AOI layer/LakePalcacocha.gdb database.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the editor toolbar, click create features&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on AOI to bring up the construction tools&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Circle tool to create a small circle that encompasses the entirety of the lake.  It is alright for our purposes if we include land area, but do not make it so large that it might include nearby lakes.  This should look something like so:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02Picture03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the editor and stop editing.  Save your edits when it prompts you to.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculating-ndwi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculating NDWI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The NWDI is defined as the normalized difference of the Green and Near Infrared bands of the Thematic Mapper.  (See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01431169608948714&#34;&gt;McFeeters paper in the International Journal Of Remote Sensing&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
$$NDWI = \frac{Green-NIR}{Green+NIR}$$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will use the raster calculator tool to accomplish this. At this point we can also use the environmental settings to clip our data so we don’t process the whole scene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under workspace, point the Current and Scratch workspaces to our LakePalcacocha.gdb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under processing extent, set the extent to “Same as Layer AOI”.  Click OK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the search bar to pull up the Raster Calculator and use the prompts to calculate the NDWI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extension warnings?  Did you take the time to read it?  Warnings are a chance to learn something and in this case you should learn that you need to turn on spatial analysis under Customize &amp;gt; Extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go ahead and try to enter in the expression above.  Save the resulting raster using the folder icon under the Output Raster dialog box, click on the name of one of the other bands (to preserve the LANDSAT naming convention), and change the end of the file to &lt;em&gt;…NDWI.tif&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that the resulting raster has a value of 0, and is entirely empty.  This is because ArcMap likes to save memory and forces raster calculations to integers.  Fixing this just means we need to be more verbose and run the calculations as floats using Float() under the Math section.  This conversion to integer occurs in both the numerator and denominator, so the float needs to wrap both of them separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you double click on the last tool run, it will open the tool prompt as it was run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the expression to:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;mark&gt;&lt;em&gt;Float(&amp;ldquo;LT05…B 2.TIF&amp;rdquo; -  &amp;ldquo;LT05…B4.TIF&amp;rdquo;) / Float(&amp;ldquo;LT05…B2.TIF&amp;rdquo; + &amp;ldquo;LT05…B4.TIF&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculating-mndwi&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculating MNDWI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The MNWDI is defined as the normalized difference of the Green and Near Infrared bands of the Thematic Mapper.  (See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/01431160600589179&#34;&gt;Xu paper, also in the International Journal Of Remote Sensing&lt;/a&gt;)
$$MNDWI = \frac{Green-MIR}{Green+MIR}$$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because this process is so similar to the NDWI (we use band 5, not band 4), it is easiest to pull the results up from our last raster calculator and change a few characters.  Change all 4’s to 5’s and change the output file name to MNDWI.&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to geoprocessing &amp;gt; Results and double click on the last tool run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;classifying-and-quantifying-the-change-in-water-surface-area&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classifying and quantifying the change in water surface area&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’ve probably noticed by now, but the NDWI and MNDWI calculations return an image with valid values from -1 to 1, but this doesn’t tell us what is and is not water.  To do that we need to classify the image into a binary water/not water schema.  There are a variety of ways to do this that range in sophistication/robustness, but for our purposes, a simple threshold will suffice.  This means we want classify all pixels with a NDWI/MNDWI value greater than or less than some value into water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the identify button and poke around the image to find a good threshold.  I settled on 0.30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the raster calculator to select the cells greater than 0.30, and append the name of the NDWI layer with the threshold value (_…NDWI&lt;em&gt;3.tif&lt;/em&gt;).
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02Picture04.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
Examine the outputs (right click on the resulting layer and see the attribute table.)  You now have enough information to answer Questions 1 - 3 above.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-simple-landsat-composites&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Simple Landsat Composites&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-composite-image&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a composite image&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the downfalls that plague many passive remote sensing platforms is the inability to penetrate cloud cover.  Notice that although we didn’t happen to encounter cloud obfuscation in the first part of this lab, clouds are not uncommon.  Let’s use water year 2005 as an example.  I’ve taken the liberty of downloading and setting up your ArcMap document and data for you.  Just download the Map package and double click to open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because land/water has a lower reflectance across all bands as opposed to clouds, one of the simplest and most effective means of filtering out cloud cover is to take the local minimum from a raster stack.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ArcMap has a tool called &lt;strong&gt;Cell Statistics&lt;/strong&gt; which performs statistics for local operations.  Either use the search tool or find it in Spatial Analyst Tools &amp;gt; local.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to calculate the minimum of each band within the 4 seasons.  Using band 4 for the winter as an example, the inputs should look like so:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02Picture05.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have gone ahead and taken the minimum of 3 of the 4 seasons. So you only need to calculate the minimums for the spring months.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform the NDWI calculation, thresholding, and area measurement as was performed above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer questions 4 and 5 in the handout.  Save and close Arcmap, we’re done looking at the lake for now.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3-cartographic-modeling&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Cartographic Modeling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;establishing-the-model-parameters&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Establishing the model parameters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start ArcMap and add &lt;i&gt;sanpre25k&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;usfrost25k&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;sample1&lt;/i&gt; from your lab02\Part03 folder.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extracting data for building Kudzu distribution model.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the attribute table for &lt;em&gt;sample1&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The numbers in the “KUDZU” field represent presence or absence of Kudzu at that point (1 for presence, 0 for absence)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want to find the minimum annual precipitation (in mm) and the minimum frost-free days at each of these points. This information will be your source of input for modeling potential Kudzu distribution across the U.S.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close the attribute table.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ArcToolbox contains an &lt;strong&gt;Extract values to points&lt;/strong&gt; tool that will add the value of a raster to a set of points. It then creates a new point file with an attribute holding that raster value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Spatial Analyst Toolbox &amp;gt;Extraction &amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Extract values to points&lt;/strong&gt; tool.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This tool requires three inputs and has two optional ones. You can find out more information about each of the inputs (this applies to other ArcTools as well) by clicking on the Show Help button and then clicking on the field of interest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your Input point features to sample1 (You can either use the drop-down that shows all the point layers in the ArcMap Table of Contents or the Browse file button to navigate to the file).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your Input raster to &lt;em&gt;usanpre25k&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set Output point features so that it saves the new file called sample1precip to your lab02\Part03 folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click OK (Be patient. This may take a while.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your new point file will appear in the ArcMap Table of Contents.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the attribute table for &lt;em&gt;sample1precip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice the new variable called RASTERVALU that contains the annual precipitation amount for that point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat the above steps&lt;/strong&gt; to create a similar point file containing a RASTERVALU attribute for frost-free days at each point. Call it &lt;em&gt;sample1frost&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, there is an &lt;strong&gt;Extract multi values to points&lt;/strong&gt; tool, which will do this whole process at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By looking at the minimum precipitation and minimum number of frost-free days that Kudzu required for survival in the sample points, we can model (predict) its potential geographic expansion across the U.S. In order to do this, we need to get this information out of the datasets we just created.  To find the minimum annual precipitation and minimum number of frost-free days required for Kudzu to survive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the attribute tables of your samples and perform an attribute query to select only those points with known Kudzu presence (“KUDZU” = 1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show only the selected records using the table toggle button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sort in ascending order the RASTERVALU field (R-Click on column heading).
Answer #6 and #7 on your answer sheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-the-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running the model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create new grids based on the usanpre25k and usfrost25k grid using Raster Calculator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;usanpre25k&lt;/i&gt; &amp;gt;= minimum value&lt;/mark&gt;** (**Minimum Value in question 6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the &lt;i&gt;usanpre25k&lt;/i&gt;, the new grid cells with an annual precipitation greater than or equal to the minimum annual precipitation will have a value of 1, while cells with an annual precipitation less than the minimum value will have a value of 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the grid as precipitation in your lab02\part03 folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;usfrost25k&lt;/i&gt; &amp;gt;= minimum value&lt;/mark&gt;** (**Minimum Value in question 7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the &lt;i&gt;usfrost25k&lt;/i&gt;, the new grid cells with a frost-free-days greater than or equal to the minimum frost-free-days will have a value of 1, while cells with a frost-free-days less than the minimum frost-free-days will have a value of 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the grid as frost in your lab02\part03 folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predict the Kudzu U.S. distribution by multiplying the precipitation and frost grids. Save the output grid as &lt;i&gt;kudzu_model&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Answer #8 on your answer sheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assessing-the-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessing the model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;i&gt;sample2&lt;/i&gt; to your ArcMap Table of Contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the Extract values to points tool you now want to create a new point shapefile called &lt;i&gt;sample2check&lt;/i&gt; that will have an attribute of actual presence (KUDZU) and one for predicted presence (RASTERVALU found by using &lt;i&gt;kudzu_model&lt;/i&gt; as raster input)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you have created &lt;i&gt;sample2check&lt;/i&gt; you can quantify your accuracy in one of many ways.  Here are two suggestions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a new field named check and perform the following calculation: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;em&gt;check = [RASTERVALU] * 10 + [KUDZU]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;.  The Check field should have the following outputs: 0, 1, 10, and 11 (0 and 1 represent 00 and 01 respectively)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform attribute query using the AND operator 4 times, once for each possible combination.  (i.g. &lt;mark&gt;&lt;em&gt;KUDZU = 1 AND RASTERVALUE = 0&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;)
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete #9 and #10 on your assignment sheet and TURN IT IN; your grade on this lab will be based entirely on your answers to the questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint: Need help answering question 10?  Make a map like so!  Useful tools: Raster to polygon, symbology as categories, rectangle as text, insert images.  If performance is an issue, add basemaps last.  Spend some time on the map and I&amp;rsquo;ll count that as a response to the question, so throw on a nice album (one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/album/72b7KBNzYH54BtZ5FBSFqi&#34;&gt;my current favorites&lt;/a&gt;) and cartography away!
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab02CartMap.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab03/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-3-focal-operations-focal-operations-removing-dem-errors-wind-exposure-and-lake-edge-detection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 3: Focal Operations – Focal Operations, Removing DEM Errors, Wind Exposure, and Lake Edge Detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objectives&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lab will use neighborhood operators (i.e. focal operators) to examine an elevation surface, remove errors in a DEM, analyze wind exposure, and delineate the edge of our lake classified in Lab 2.  In the first part, you will learn how to bring an ASCII into Arc as a grid and confirm your understanding of focal statistics.  In the second, you will use the slope tool and focal statistics to blur out errors in the DEM and examine how changing the window results in a changing image.  In Part 3, you will perform a site suitability analysis for wind turbines using the slope, aspect, hillshade, and focal wedge tools.  Finally, we will use focal erosion to isolate the edge of our lakes classified in Lab 2.  You can do all of these parts within the same or separate mxd’s, but be sure to save often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 3:  Focal Operations Assignment: Focal Operations, Removing DEM Errors, Wind Exposure, and Lake Edge Detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Name:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Use your test raster layer to run the following three FOCAL operations (with a rectangular neighborhood of 3 by 3, cell size 10) and fill in the respective grids:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focal Sum: test_sum:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focal Maximum: test_max:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focal Mean: test_mean:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-td&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 2&lt;/strong&gt;: What was the size of the patches used to mosaic the image? (approximately):  _______  Meters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 3&lt;/strong&gt;: Are the artifacts (errors) still visible in silver3x3 and silver7x7?:  _______ (true/false)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 4&lt;/strong&gt;: How many cells have an elevation greater than or equal to 1000m?:  _______ Cells&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 5&lt;/strong&gt;: How many cells have an aspect between 225&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; and 315&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; (see your GoodAspect raster layer)?  _______ cells&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 6&lt;/strong&gt;: What is the total area (m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) of Good sites and blocked cells using a 10 cell radius (see your GoodSites10 raster layer)?&lt;br /&gt;
Good Sites:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blocked:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 7&lt;/strong&gt;: Calculate wind exposure using a wedge radius of 4 cells (120 meters).  Use similar naming conventions (i.e: WindMean04, GoodWindExp04, GoodSites04, &amp;amp; Blocked04).  What is the total area (m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) of the good sites and blocked cells?&lt;br /&gt;
Good Sites:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blocked:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 8&lt;/strong&gt;: Calculate wind exposure using a wedge radius of 20 cells (600 meters).  Use similar naming conventions (i.e: WindMean20, GoodWindExp20, GoodSites20, &amp;amp; Blocked20).  What is the total area (m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) of the good sites and blocked cells?&lt;br /&gt;
Good Sites:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Blocked:  _______ m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extra Point&lt;/strong&gt;:  Why did increasing the radius value to 20 in question 8 cause the wedge neighborhood computation time to increase so dramatically? (look at the time spent in geoprocessing &amp;gt; results)  Be specific; only the best answers will get the full point!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question 9&lt;/strong&gt;: Paste your final map here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kansas-my.sharepoint.com/:f:/g/personal/j610c377_home_ku_edu/EpAWoaa4PlxPortOB7jO9o0BV8Bg5ykTI4mdEj5bsjTObg?e=OcDxTg&#34;&gt;click to download&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Relevant part&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Test.txt&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;ASCII Grid with sample values&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;silvrsub_f  &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;DEM for Silverton, CO (30m cell size, elevation in feet)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;wnw&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;DEM of NW part of Watauga Cnty (30m cell size, elevation in feet)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;BaseData&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Data downloaded in the first lab&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 4&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;NDWI_3.tif&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;NDWI threshold maps you created in Lab 2&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-focal-operation-test&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Focal Operation Test&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;converting-the-ascii-file-to-a-grid-and-run-focal-tools&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Converting the ASCII file to a grid and run focal tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcMap and make sure that the Spatial Analyst extension is activated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Name the default data frame to ASCII Grid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the workspace for the Spatial Analyst Tools by going to Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Environments…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under Workspace change the Current Workspace to your Lab3 folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename the data frame named ASCII Grid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspect the ASCII Grid file &lt;i&gt;test.txt&lt;/i&gt; using a text editor such as notepad. We will use this small raster file to visually verify the results of several focal operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcToolbox and Select Conversion Tools | To Raster | &lt;strong&gt;ASCII to Raster&lt;/strong&gt; tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set test.txt as the input file and save the output raster as test in your lab03\part01 folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave the data type to default and Click OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The test raster will be added to the Table of Contents automatically.  You can ignore any projection warnings you receive when adding these rasters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the ArcToolbox | Spatial Analyst Tools | Neighborhood | &lt;strong&gt;Focal Statistics&lt;/strong&gt; tool to answer Question #1 on your assignment sheet.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hint #1: change your layer symbology to show unique values.
hint#2: Want to flex?  You can label the rasters as shown below, and it&amp;rsquo;s good cartography practice.
Useful tools: Raster to points/extract values to points, label placement and halos, field representation to round to two decimal places.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab03CartPic1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save your Arcmap document.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-removing-dem-errors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Removing DEM Errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;convert-dem-from-feet-to-meters&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Convert DEM from feet to meters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s lay down the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert and rename a data frame to DEM Error Removal.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;i&gt;silvrsub_f&lt;/i&gt; grid to the data frame.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This surface was created in rectangular patches and then mosaiced together, but the artifacts of mosaicing are not readily visible by simply viewing the DEM.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the height is in feet and the cell sizes are in meters, you should put everything into the same unit using a local operation (i.e., Raster Calculator).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint: 1 foot = 0.3048 meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output to your lab03\part02 folder as: &lt;i&gt;silversub_m&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;locate-artifacts-errors-in-the-dem&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locate Artifacts (Errors) in the DEM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by calculating the slope for the raster to more easily identify the artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcToopbox | Spatial Analyst Tools | Surface | &lt;strong&gt;Slope&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a focal operation we can use to find the linear artifacts in the &lt;i&gt;silversub_m&lt;/i&gt; grid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the slope dialog box, set the input raster as &lt;i&gt;silversub_m&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave the default values for output measurement and z factor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output grid &lt;i&gt;silver_slope&lt;/i&gt; in your lab03\part02 folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now be able to visually pick out the linear artifacts left from the mosaicing process.  Using the measurement tool, determine the approximate size of the patches that were used to mosaic the image and answer Question #2 on your assignment sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;removing-dem-errors&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removing DEM Errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now try to eliminate the artifacts by smoothing the surface of &lt;i&gt;silversub_m&lt;/i&gt; before deriving the slope.  Go to ArcToolbox | Spatial Analyst Tools | Neighborhood | &lt;strong&gt;Focal Statistics&lt;/strong&gt; to compute the mean elevation value in a rectangular neighborhood of 3x3 cells and another of 7x7 cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use silversub_m as the input in both cases, making sure to name the output appropriately, something like &lt;i&gt;silver3x3&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;silver7x7&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derive the slopes of these new surfaces as in step 2, and be sure to name them appropriately, something like &lt;i&gt;slope3x3&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;slope7x7&lt;/i&gt; respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer Question #3 on your assignment sheet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3-wind-exposure-analysis&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Wind Exposure Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;convert-dem-from-feet-to-meters-1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Convert DEM from feet to meters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s lay down the foundation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert a new dataframe and call it Wind Exposure Analysis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;i&gt;wnw&lt;/i&gt; grid to the data frame.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This surface was created in rectangular patches and then mosaiced together, but the artifacts of mosaicing are not readily visible by simply viewing the DEM.  Since the height is in feet and the cell sizes are in meters, you should put everything into the same unit, as was done in Part 2. Save the output to your lab03\part03 folder as: &lt;i&gt;wnm_m&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;obtaining-areas-with-good-elevation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obtaining Areas with Good Elevation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the cells where the elevation in &lt;i&gt;wnw_m&lt;/i&gt; is greater than or equal to 1000m by creating the following expression in the Raster Calculator: &lt;mark&gt;“wnw_m” &amp;gt;= 1000&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the output raster a permanent layer named &lt;i&gt;GoodElevation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;generating-a-hillshade-raster-layer&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating a Hillshade raster layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Spatial Analyst, create a hillshade raster from your &lt;i&gt;wnw_m&lt;/i&gt; DEM using the ArcToolbox | Spatial Analyst Tools | Surface | &lt;strong&gt;Hillshade&lt;/strong&gt; tool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;i&gt;wnw_m&lt;/i&gt; as your input surface, leave the default settings for azimuth and altitude, but set the Z factor to 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output grid as &lt;i&gt;hillshade&lt;/i&gt; in your lab03\part03 folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;visualizing-with-hillshade&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualizing with hillshade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiilshades are useful for providing geographic context, but can overwhelm data which kind of defeats the purpose of making a map.  One way to fix this is mask out no data values in your output layer, and make it slightly transparent.  We&amp;rsquo;ll do this a few times in this lab so remember this sequence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display &lt;i&gt;GoodElevation&lt;/i&gt; on top of &lt;i&gt;hillshade&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the color of the bad elevations (0’s) to hollow (no color) by:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R-clicking on &lt;i&gt;GoodElivation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select symbology tab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check box “display background value:”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proceed with: 0 symbol and selecting No Color.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the Transparency value of &lt;i&gt;GoodElivation&lt;/i&gt; to approximately 40%

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R-Click -&amp;gt; Properties under the Display tab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer Question #4 on your assignment sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;obtaining-areas-with-good-aspect&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obtaining Areas with Good Aspect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate the aspect from &lt;i&gt;wnw_m&lt;/i&gt; DEM using the ArcToolbox | Spatial Analyst Tools| Surface | &lt;strong&gt;Aspect&lt;/strong&gt; tool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output grid as aspect in your lab03\part03 folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice the range of angles assigned to each direction in the table of contents. Aspect values begin at 0 at due north and increase clockwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Raster Calculator, select the cells with an aspect between 225&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt; and 315&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;. This will give us the westward facing slopes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That expression should look like &lt;mark&gt;(225 &amp;lt;= “aspect”) &amp;amp; (“aspect” &amp;lt;= 315)&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the output raster a layer named &lt;i&gt;GoodAspect&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display the &lt;i&gt;GoodAspect&lt;/i&gt; on top of &lt;i&gt;hillshade&lt;/i&gt; (set symbology like you did for &lt;i&gt;GoodElivation&lt;/i&gt;) and verify that it represents the western slopes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer Question #5 on your assignment sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;obtaining-wind-exposure-values&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obtaining Wind Exposure Values&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a neighbor mean raster of &lt;i&gt;wnw_m&lt;/i&gt; using a FocalMean operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ArcToolbox | Spatial Analyst Tools | Neighborhood | Focal Statistics with a wedge neighborhood (start angle 135, end angle 225, and a radius of 10 cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note here that the wedge neighborhood is measured differently than the aspect. The aspect measurement begins at 0 degrees due north and increases as we move clockwise. However, when computing a wedge neighborhood, we start at 0 degrees due east and increase as we move counterclockwise. Thus, the degree range here (135-225) represents the same degree range as indicated in the aspect range (225-315). This is simply due to inconsistencies in the way the ArcGIS software handles radial measurements.  TODO: Add a nice image of this here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;WindMean10&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Raster Calculator, select the cells whose elevations are higher than their neighbor mean (i.e., &lt;em&gt;WindMean10&lt;/em&gt;)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;_wnw&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;WindMean10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the output a permanent raster named &lt;i&gt;GoodWindExp10&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display &lt;em&gt;GoodWindExp10&lt;/em&gt; on top of &lt;i&gt;hillshade&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;isolate-the-best-sites-and-those-that-meet-all-the-criteria-except-wind-exposure&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isolate the best sites and those that meet all the criteria except wind exposure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Raster Calculator, select the cells with good elevation (1’s), aspect (1’s), and wind exposure (1’s).  Your expression can look like: &lt;mark&gt;(&lt;em&gt;GoodElevation&lt;/em&gt; == 1) &amp;amp; (&lt;em&gt;GoodAspect&lt;/em&gt; == 1) &amp;amp; (&lt;em&gt;GoodWindExp10&lt;/em&gt; == 1)&lt;/mark&gt;, or more simply &lt;mark&gt;&lt;em&gt;GoodElevation&lt;/em&gt; * &lt;em&gt;GoodAspect&lt;/em&gt; * &lt;em&gt;GoodWindExp10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the output a permanent raster named &lt;i&gt;GoodSites10&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Raster Calculator, select the cells with good elevation (1’s), good aspect (1’s) and bad wind exposure (0’s) with the following expression: &lt;mark&gt;(&lt;em&gt;GoodElevation&lt;/em&gt; == 1) &amp;amp; (&lt;em&gt;GoodAspect&lt;/em&gt; == 1) &amp;amp; (&lt;em&gt;GoodWindExp10&lt;/em&gt; == 0)&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make this a permanent raster named &lt;i&gt;Blocked10&lt;/i&gt;, which indicate cells where the wind is blocked because of hills to the west.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer questions #6 - #8 on your assignment sheet (you will need to repeat the steps above twice more using different radius values)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-4-lake-edge-detection&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 4: Lake Edge Detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open your Lab 2 Part 1 mxd or create a data frame/document.  This document should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;AOI&lt;/em&gt; shapefile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lake body classifications (&lt;i&gt;…NDWI_#.TIF&lt;/i&gt;) )for 1995, 2003, and 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The RGB file for each year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-boundary-of-the-lake-in-1995-using-a-focal-erosion-process&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the boundary of the lake in 1995 using a focal erosion process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;strong&gt;Focal statistics&lt;/strong&gt; tool, calculate the focal minimum using a rectangular 3x3 grid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The input should be the &lt;i&gt;…_NDWI_3.TIF&lt;/i&gt; created in Lab 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output in the 1995 BaseData folder and name the output as &lt;i&gt;…_NDWI_FMin.TIF&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-difference-between-the-two-surfaces&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the difference between the two surfaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using raster calculator, subtract the focal min raster from the lake classification raster using an expression such as: &lt;mark&gt;&amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;em&gt;L1TP&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;_NDWI_3.TIF&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;em&gt;L1TP&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;_NDWI_FMin.TIF&amp;rdquo;&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output of the map as &lt;i&gt;LT05_&amp;hellip;_LakeBoundry.TIF&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perform-the-above-steps-for-both-2003-and-2009&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perform the above steps for both 2003 and 2009&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;make-a-small-map-like-so&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a small map like so&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move to layout view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the page dimensions to 11 in x 11 (File, page and print setup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use guides to set up 3 inch grids (click on the guides)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on the data frames to copy them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste them in the frame and rename them to the appropriate place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text can be rotated in the properties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To add grid lines, change the frame properties or using lines by adding the drawing toolbar (right click in the grey area as necessary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, export your map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab03Picture01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab04/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-4-zonal-operations-tornado-siren-coverage-analysis-and-lake-volume-calculations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 4: Zonal Operations – Tornado Siren Coverage Analysis and Lake Volume Calculations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this lab, we are interested in assessing how much of Douglas County is covered by tornado sirens. In other words, we want to know how many people can actually hear a tornado siren when it goes off. While the sirens for Douglas County were designed to be heard at distances of up to 5,800 feet, there might be areas in which people can’t hear them.
Finally, we will use the zonal definitions of lake area created in lab 3 to calculate the height of the water from the DEM and turn the height and area into a volume estimation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 4: Answer Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Name:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Total Douglas County population:&lt;br /&gt;
Number of people who can hear the tornado sirens:&lt;br /&gt;
Number of people who cannot hear the tornado sirens:&lt;br /&gt;
Percentage of the population that can hear the tornado sirens:&lt;br /&gt;
Percentage of total population that cannot hear the tornado sirens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Your math should add up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
How much water did the lake gain over the time period:&lt;br /&gt;
Which period did the volume grow the fastest, 1995-2003 or 2003-2009?&lt;br /&gt;
Write a short (2-4 healthy paragraphs) analysis regarding this process.  Some topics to touch on include how this analysis was performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you expect a significantly different answer if you tweaked the methods?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the sources of error in this process?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we address those, and the uncertainty they add to our analysis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kansas-my.sharepoint.com/:f:/g/personal/j610c377_home_ku_edu/ElqTq-WOUl1KrxdPWkMRJGkBS9BI9yWgsfjoAvXWacKleA?e=f22wwF&#34;&gt;click to download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Relevant part&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;censusblk.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;ensus blocks for Douglas County, Kansas&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;kansas2000censusblk.dbf&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Database file containing census data, including population per block group&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;sirens.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Point shapefile with locations of tornado sirens in Douglas County, KS&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;roads.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Douglas County Roads&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;countybnd.shp&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Douglas County Boundary&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;BaseData&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Data downloaded in the first lab&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;…LakeBoundry.tif&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;NDWI threshold maps for 1995, 2003, and 2009&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-tornado-siren-coverage&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Tornado siren coverage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-buffers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create Buffers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In ArcMap, create a new empty map, and save your map document to your personal folder.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;i&gt;countybnd.shp&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;roads.shp&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;censusblk.shp&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;sirens.shp&lt;/i&gt; from your Part1 folder to the empty arcmap.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create buffers around the sirens using the &lt;strong&gt;buffer&lt;/strong&gt; tool and the following settings:&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input Features: &lt;em&gt;sirens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output Features: &lt;i&gt;sirens_buffer.shp&lt;/i&gt; (make sure to save in your Part1 folder)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linear Unit: 5800 feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolve Type: None&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrange layers so that you can see the siren points and buffers on top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let’s remove the common polygon lines in the buffers. In ArcToolbox go to Data Management Tools | Generalization | &lt;strong&gt;Dissolve&lt;/strong&gt;. Use the following settings:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input Features: &lt;i&gt;sirens_buffer&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output Features: &lt;i&gt;sirens_buffer_dissolve.shp&lt;/i&gt; (make sure to save in your Part1 folder)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the symbology of the layers to the colors and symbols of your choice, and arrange the layers accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that you could have just used the dissolve type parameter in the buffer tool, but now you know where both are :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-the-percentage-of-population-covered-by-sirens&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finding the Percentage of Population Covered by Sirens&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;i&gt;kansas2000censusblk.dbf&lt;/i&gt; to the data frame.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click the &lt;i&gt;censusblk&lt;/i&gt; layer, select Joins and Relates, and select Join. Join the layer to &lt;i&gt;kansas2000censusblk.dbf&lt;/i&gt; using the STFID field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine the attribute table of &lt;i&gt;censusblk&lt;/i&gt; to make sure the join was successful. Do you see all sorts of demographic attributes? If so, the join was successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab04imageJoin.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: Need a refresher on joins?  Try &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog358/lab06/&#34;&gt;lab 6 from the intro class&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click the header of the &lt;i&gt;POP2000&lt;/i&gt; attribute and select Statistics. The sum value is the number of people in Douglas County. Record the value somewhere, as you will be entering this into the comments section of your Blackboard submission. Close the window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Select by Location… to select the census blocks that are within the buffer zone.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: Use the are completely within the source layer feature setting. The result should be 1,590 census blocks selected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the population in these census blocks by opening the &lt;i&gt;censusblk&lt;/i&gt; attribute table, right- clicking the &lt;i&gt;POP2000&lt;/i&gt; attribute header, and selecting Statistics. (It will only give you statistics on the selected records.) Record this number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find the population out of the range of sirens by clicking Table Options (upper left corner of the attribute table), selecting Switch Selection, and then using the &lt;strong&gt;Statistics&lt;/strong&gt; tool again. Record this number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch the selection back (i.e., back to the blocks within range of the sirens) and close the attribute table.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer the part 1 questions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-lake-volume-estimations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Lake Volume estimations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open your Lab 2 Part 1 mxd or create a data frame/document.  This document should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AOI shapefile.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lake boundary classifications &lt;i&gt;(…NDWI_#.TIF)&lt;/i&gt; )for 1995, 2003, and 2009.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The RGB file for each year&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elevation data&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;isolate-the-lake-boundary&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isolate the lake boundary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have already noticed, we need to isolate the lake boundary from any errant, misclassified pixels.  We can do that a few different ways you can do this.  For each image, redefine an AOI and use the raster clip to isolate the lake boundary.  This is time consuming unsalable, and poorly reproducible.  Here we will deploy a focal approach.  Note that here, your numbers will differ from mine, region groups applies group numbers in a quasi-random fashion, and you may or may not have the same number of groups that I do.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab04image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more preferable way to do this is to use region groups, a tool you will cover in much more depth later in the semester.  For now, just know that it groups clusters of raster pixels into unique groups.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;i&gt;…LakeBoundary.tif&lt;/i&gt; as the input raster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output raster as &lt;i&gt;…groups.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Eight connectivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the identify tool to pick out the value of the lake edge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the raster calculator to create a zone of just that value.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: mine looks like &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;LT05_L1TP_008067_19950622_20170109_01_T1_LakeBoundry_Group.TIF&amp;rdquo; == 10&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overwrite&lt;/strong&gt; your lake boundary raster&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-height-the-water-rises-to-on-the-terrain&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the height the water rises to on the terrain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use zonal statistics and our newly created zone to calculate the (insert statistic here) value of the elevation data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the newly created lake boundary as our zonal definition.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want the statistics from the elevation data.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a statistic, I chose maximum but feel free to explore other options.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;…LakeBoundary_ZonalStat.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This output is the “elevation” of the water, we then need to place this value in a raster that we can subtract from the DEM to calculate a lake depth at each pixel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-the-lake-surface-elevation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create the lake surface elevation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to use the same process as above to pick out just the lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;(&amp;ldquo;…LakeBoundry_Group.TIF&amp;rdquo; == 10) | (&amp;ldquo;…LakeBoundry_Group.TIF&amp;rdquo; == 12)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: That&amp;rsquo;s an | above, not a /.  The &amp;ldquo;pipe&amp;rdquo; is computer shortcode for &amp;ldquo;OR&amp;rdquo;.  Shift backslash on most keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;…LakeRaster.tif&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then need to use the reclassify tool to turn the binary lake classification into a lake elevation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn 0’s into NoData.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn 1’s into the value of the zonal statistic output calculated in the previous step.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;…LakeSurface.tif&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab04image2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-lake-depth-and-the-lake-volume&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the lake depth and the lake volume&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We now need to subtract our two surfaces&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: RasterCalcuator(lakeSurface – Elevation)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;…LakeDepth.tif&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Examine the attribute table of the subtraction grid (&lt;strong&gt;R-click&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth&lt;/i&gt; | &lt;strong&gt;Open Attribute Table&lt;/strong&gt;).
&lt;li&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Select by Attribute&lt;/strong&gt; button and select cells with an elevation difference greater than 0.
&lt;li&gt;Export selected cells &lt;strong&gt;(Table Options | Export…)&lt;/strong&gt; as a dBASE Table file named &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995.dbf&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;li&gt;When asked if you want to add the table to your map, select Yes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there were no errors but you cannot see &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995.dbf&lt;/i&gt; in your Table of Contents, you  need to switch to List By Source view&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Open &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995.dbf&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(R-click | Open)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a new field &lt;strong&gt;(Table Options | Add Field)&lt;/strong&gt; and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set the name to &lt;i&gt;Area&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type to float&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;precision to 16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale to 1 and then click OK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Calculate the surface area of &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995&lt;/i&gt; using the following equation, &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;area = # of cells (count) * length of cell * width of cell&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint #1: (R-click column to be calculated, choose Field Calculator… if asked about calculating outside an Editing session, click Yes)
&lt;br&gt;
Hint #2: the length and width of the cell comes from the cell size of the grid, since the cells are square, the values are the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Add a new field and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set the name to &lt;i&gt;cell_vol&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type to float&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;precision to 16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale to 1 and then click OK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;li&gt;Calculate the volume per cell of &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995&lt;/i&gt; using the following equation: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;cell_vol = depth (i.e., Value) * length of cell * width of cell&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a new field and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set the name to &lt;i&gt;total_vol&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type to float&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;precision to 16&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale to 1 and then click OK
&lt;li&gt;Calculate the total volume of &lt;i&gt;LakeDepth1995&lt;/i&gt; using the following equation: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;total_vol = volume per cell (cell_vol) * total number of cells (count)&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to perform this process twice more for 2003 and 2009, answer the part 2 questions, and submit both parts to Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab05/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-5-model-builder&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 5 - Model Builder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have likely noticed, the process of delineating a lake follows a predictable workflow that could easily be automated, and because time is money, it would behoove us to create a script one could run which would create the needed outputs for us without all the tedious clicking and typing that would otherwise have to occur.  Fortunately, ArcGIS has a mode, Model Builder, which enables us to visually create a workflow to connect our data to a series of Operations without the need to actually code in python.  To do this effectively, we need to modify our process somewhat, so the first part of this lab will walk us through the steps needed to perform this analysis on a single year, and part 2 will introduce the model builder interface and how this process can be automated and applied to each year we downloaded in lab 1.  By the end of this lab you should have a firm grasp on the local, focal and zonal operations we need to use to create the lake, and how model builder can be used in numerous applications to speed up your workflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit an image of both your analysis and a screenshot of your model to blackboard.  Then submit your screenshot to this Google Sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;BaseData&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Data we downloaded as part of lab 1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-performing-our-analysis-for-one-year&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Performing our analysis for one year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1a-setting-up-arcmap&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1A: Setting up Arcmap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-set-up&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting set up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s lay down the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcMap and make sure that the Spatial Analyst extension is activated, and overwriting files is enabled.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Customize &amp;gt; Extensions&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;ArcMap options&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename the default data frame to Base Data and add in the AOI, Bands 2 and 4, and the MTL file for each year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To force our model to calculate everything using a consistent grid size, change the Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Environments settings to the following:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workspace&lt;/strong&gt;: Set both the Current workspace and Scratch workspaces to your lab05 folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processing Extent&lt;/strong&gt;: Use the folder icon and point it to your AOI shapefile.  Use the folder icon next to snap raster to select the elevation dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raster Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Select As specified below and type in 30.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you discovered in lab 4, the &lt;strong&gt;region group&lt;/strong&gt; tool was useful in creating a raster we could use to select the desired areas.  However, the region values were random.  Although we could in theory make a program and so this will not work if we are attempting to create a programmatic workflow.  We will instead use a “seed” and the cost distance tool to classify which of the NDWI zones we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-the-lakeseed-shapefile&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create the LakeSeed shapefile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the ArcCatalogue window right click on the Lab 5 folder and create a new feature class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call the class LakeSeed and make it a point feature.  Click next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Layers box to select the correct projection.  Click next until you reach the Field Names category.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the first empty Field Name box, type in VALUE and change the Data Type to Short Integer.  In the field properties you can set the default value to 1.  Click Finish.  The layer should be added to your window.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Editor toolbar, click Editor &amp;gt; Start Editing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Create Features window, click LakeSeed and choose the point tool.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a single feature that will “intersect” all lake layers through time, so the center of the smallest lake extent is best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When finished, click editor &amp;gt;  stop editing and save edits.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab05Picture01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1b-isolate-the-lake&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1B: Isolate the lake&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-and-threshold-ndwi-in-one-expression&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate and threshold NDWI (in one expression)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall from lab 2 that this expression needs appropriate parenthesis and the Float() attribute.  However, we want to reverse the expression here so that &lt;strong&gt;we want to classify as a lake has a 0 vale, and everything else has a value of 1&lt;/strong&gt;.  This way we can use the cost distance tool to traverse all connected lake pixels without inuring a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: My expression looks like &lt;/br&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Float(&amp;ldquo;1995\LT05_&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;B2.TIF&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;B4.TIF&amp;rdquo;) / Float(&amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;em&gt;B2.TIF&amp;rdquo; + &amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;_B4.TIF&amp;rdquo;))  &amp;lt;= 0.3&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call the output &lt;i&gt;NDWI_yyyy&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-the-lakeseed-to-isolate-just-the-ndwi-zone-we-want&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the LakeSeed to isolate just the NDWI zone we want&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the search bar to find the &lt;strong&gt;Cost Distance&lt;/strong&gt; tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source data is the &lt;i&gt;LakeSeedRas&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The input cost raster is the &lt;i&gt;NDWI_1995&lt;/i&gt; layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;COST_1995&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To save ourselves a step, we can set the maximum distance to 0.01(something small), so that we only end up with the lake area that can be reached without crossing a land barrier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want just the lake, so use raster calculator and get just the areas with 0 cost

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Cost_yyyy.tif” ==0&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the raster as &lt;i&gt;Lake_yyyy.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1c-lake-volume-calculation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1C: Lake volume calculation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-boundary-of-the-lake-in-1995-using-a-focal-erosion-process&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the boundary of the lake in 1995 using a focal erosion process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(as per lab 3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;strong&gt;Focal statistics&lt;/strong&gt; tool, calculate the focal minimum using a rectangular 3x3 grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The input should be the &lt;i&gt;Lake_1995&lt;/i&gt; layer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output &lt;i&gt;Lake_Fmin.TIF&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;strong&gt;raster calculator&lt;/strong&gt;, subtract the focal min raster from the lake classification raster to get just the boundary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;em&gt;L1TP&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;_NDWI_3.TIF&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;1995\LT05&lt;em&gt;L1TP&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;_NDWI_FMin.TIF&amp;rdquo;&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output of the map as &lt;i&gt;lakeEdge_1995.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-height-the-water-rises-to-on-the-terrain&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the height the water rises to on the terrain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per lab 4 we will use &lt;strong&gt;zonal statistics as table&lt;/strong&gt; and our newly created zone to calculate the (&lt;em&gt;insert statistic here&lt;/em&gt;) value of the elevation data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the lake boundary (&lt;i&gt;lakeEdge_1995.tif&lt;/i&gt;) as our zonal definition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want the statistics from the elevation data, so that goes in the “Input Value Raster” box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose a statistic, I chose maximum but feel free to explore other options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;…LakeBoundary_ZonalStat&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-the-lake-surface-raster&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create the lake surface raster&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also from lab 4 use the &lt;strong&gt;reclass by table&lt;/strong&gt; function (spatial analyst) to reclassify the &lt;i&gt;lake_1995&lt;/i&gt; raster into a lake surface raster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your input raster is &lt;i&gt;Lake_1995&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your remap table is the table created from zonal statistics as table (&lt;i&gt;LakeBoundary_ZonalStat&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The From, to, and output value should fill in asutomagically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;LakeSurface_yyyy.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need just the lake elevations, and given the tools shown so far we could accomplish that by multiplying them with the Lake_1995 raster using raster calculator (to set the values we no longer want to 0), and then setting the 0 values to NoData.  We can do this in 1 step through raster calculator using the  Set &lt;strong&gt;Null function&lt;/strong&gt;.  The &lt;strong&gt;Set Null(,)&lt;/strong&gt; function takes two arguments, a mask which sets the values to null and a raster with the values to set otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;SetNull(&amp;ldquo;%Lake_1995%&amp;rdquo; ==0, &amp;ldquo;%LakeSurface_ZS.tif%&amp;ldquo;)&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output raster as LakeSurface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculate-the-volume-as-per-lab-4&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calculate the volume (as per lab 4)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subtract the Lake Surface from the DEM using the &lt;strong&gt;raster calculator&lt;/strong&gt; tool

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;i&gt;LakeVolume.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;Add field&lt;/strong&gt; tool (data management) to create a new field

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call it volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;Calculate Field&lt;/strong&gt; tool to calculate the volume of each cell

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: Depth(Value) * area (30*30) * Count&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;summery table&lt;/strong&gt; to create a table of volume&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process was time consuming, and the only thing that changes in this workflow (once we’ve chosen a place to analyses), is the input bands.  This repetitious task is best completed using a function.  In ArcMap, functions can take the form of tools, and the visual programming interface called Model Builder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-creating-the-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PART 2: Creating the model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-the-folders-for-the-lab&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up the folders for the lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In your lab folder in the ArcCatalog pane, create a new File Geodatabase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In that same lab folder, Right click and create a new &amp;gt; toolbox.  Name it &lt;i&gt;LakeVolumeAnalysis.tbx&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right click&lt;/strong&gt; on that toolbox and create a new &amp;gt; model.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A blank Model window will appear. Take a moment to explore the tools. You can go to ArcGIS Desktop Help to find more information about each of the tools.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab05ModelBuilderImage.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close the Model window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on the model and

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the general tab rename the model &lt;i&gt;LakeVolumeForAYear&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-open the Model by R-clicking and selecting Edit…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up the Model Properties by going to &lt;strong&gt;Model | Model Properties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the Environments tab, check the boxes for &lt;strong&gt;Processing Extent | Extent&lt;/strong&gt; and for &lt;strong&gt;Raster Analysis | Cell Size&lt;/strong&gt;, and for &lt;strong&gt;Workspace&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the &lt;em&gt;Values…&lt;/em&gt; button, and set the values as in part 1A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove all layers from the map&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-a-model-setting-up-the-workflow&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starting a Model &amp;amp; Setting up the Workflow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will create a workflow diagram in the Model window that will show all the steps and operations/tools needed to delineate the sea level change. We start the process by dragging tools from ArcToolbox into the Model window to perform a specific operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcToolbox and set up your model window and ArcMap window so that you can see both ArcToolbox and the model window at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the add data button to add in the band 2 and band 4 rasters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on the resulting oval and rename it to Band 2 and 4 respectively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on it and make it a parameter by checking &lt;strong&gt;Model Parameter&lt;/strong&gt; option from its popup menu (right-click). The letter &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt; appears beside the variable, indicating it is a model parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert a new variable with insert &amp;gt; create variable

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select Double&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double click on it and give it a default value of 0.3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click on it and make it a parameter as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the search function to drag in the &lt;strong&gt;raster calculator&lt;/strong&gt; tool from ArcCatalog into the model builder canvas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double click on the raster calculator tool and fill it out as appropriate using the steps above.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you use the drop downs to populate the raster calculator, pointing at the data is not appropriate here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: My expression looks like &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Float(&amp;ldquo;%1995 B2%&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;%1995 B4%&amp;rdquo;) / Float(&amp;ldquo;%1995 B2%&amp;rdquo; + &amp;ldquo;%1995 B4%&amp;rdquo;)) &amp;lt;= float(%Double%)&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Name the output &lt;i&gt;NDWI.tif&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The bubbles should color themselves in if you entered everything in correctly.  This means that the tools executed successfully, but be careful.  Just because it ran doesn’t mean it is right.  Your model should now look like so:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab05Picture02.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-the-rest-of-the-workflow&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build the rest of the workflow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build the rest of the workflow as defined above by dragging in tools.  Your final model should look like this:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab05Picture03.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Use your new model to create a chart of the lake volume change over time like so:
 &lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab05Picture04.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Submit an image of both your analysis and a screenshot of your model to blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/lab06/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lab-6-more-model-builder&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 6 - More Model Builder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;learning-objective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Objective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lab is designed to further strengthen your understanding and ability to apply local, focal, and zonal operations to solve problems and comfortability with ModelBuilder, this time in the context of delineating sea level rize.  In part 1, you will walk through 2 methods of using the point and click interface to accomplish your analysis.  In part 2, you will use ModelBuilder to accomplish this same task, and in part 3 you will see how you can import your own python analysis into ArcMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-you-need-to-submit&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you need to submit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lab 6: Answer Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Name:&lt;br /&gt;
1 How many pixels are inundated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 While you’re building your models with model builder, you create several variables called model parameters that are shown with P letter next to their variables. What happens if you didn’t create those model parameters? What is the benefit of having the model parameters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 In part 02 of the lab, list all the output layers after you Run Entire Model in the ‘InundationByRegionGroup’ model builder window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 In part 02, how many cells does the final output have the value of ‘1’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 Which of the two methods of delineating sea level rise, region group or cost distance, was the more efficient means of performing this analysis?  Why do you think this is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 Submit a coherent map of the output.  Use mine below as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6MyMap.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 This time, double click the InundationByRegionGroupPython script tool in part 03. When the model tool dialog box is opened, fill the parameter boxes with the right layer names. Click OK to run the tool. How many output layers do you have? List them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 In part 03 how many cells does the final output have the value of ‘1’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 If the Sea Level Rise is set to 4, how many cells does the final output have the value of ‘1’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kansas-my.sharepoint.com/:f:/g/personal/j610c377_home_ku_edu/Ekw4OGrLcvJNq8K-MJiBYygBbJ-7_2l1RV4WyCTslNCt8w?e=ILAHpW&#34;&gt;click to download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;margin:0px auto;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-btxf{background-color:#f9f9f9;border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Relevant part&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1-3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;DEM&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Raster dataset of the elevation of the area&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 1-3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Ocean&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Raster dataset of the land cover types (Land &amp;amp; Ocean) over the area&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Part 3&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;SeaLevelRiseInundation.py&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Sea Level Rise inundation delineation using region group and zonal max&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-1-delineating-sea-level-rise-inundation-with-arcmap&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1: Delineating Sea Level Rise Inundation with ArcMap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you saw in class, it is possible to take two different approaches to map sea level rise in GIS.  We can use cost distance to calculate the rise from an ocean source or we can use region group to get the regions of inundation which include an ocean source.  Here you need to pick one of the methods and walk through it using ArcMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unzip the lab 6 folder into your one drive, in it you will find a baseData folder, and folders already set up for part1, part2, and part3.  Go ahead and pick a means of delineating sea level rise, either cost distance or region groups, and perform a 2-meter sea level rise analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style id=&#34;Book1_4029_Styles&#34;&gt;
&lt;!--table
    {mso-displayed-decimal-separator:&#34;\.&#34;;
    mso-displayed-thousand-separator:&#34;\,&#34;;}
.font54029
    {color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:400;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:none;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;}
.font64029
    {color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:400;
    font-style:italic;
    text-decoration:none;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;}
.xl654029
    {padding-top:1px;
    padding-right:1px;
    padding-left:1px;
    mso-ignore:padding;
    color:black;
    font-size:11.0pt;
    font-weight:400;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:none;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;
    mso-number-format:General;
    text-align:general;
    vertical-align:bottom;
    mso-background-source:auto;
    mso-pattern:auto;
    white-space:nowrap;}
.xl664029
    {padding-top:1px;
    padding-right:1px;
    padding-left:1px;
    mso-ignore:padding;
    color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:700;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:underline;
    text-underline-style:single;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;
    mso-number-format:General;
    text-align:center;
    vertical-align:middle;
    border-top:.5pt solid windowtext;
    border-right:none;
    border-bottom:1.0pt solid windowtext;
    border-left:none;
    mso-background-source:auto;
    mso-pattern:auto;
    white-space:nowrap;}
.xl674029
    {padding-top:1px;
    padding-right:1px;
    padding-left:1px;
    mso-ignore:padding;
    color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:700;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:underline;
    text-underline-style:single;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;
    mso-number-format:General;
    text-align:center;
    vertical-align:middle;
    border-top:.5pt solid windowtext;
    border-right:none;
    border-bottom:1.0pt solid windowtext;
    border-left:.5pt solid windowtext;
    mso-background-source:auto;
    mso-pattern:auto;
    white-space:nowrap;}
.xl684029
    {padding-top:1px;
    padding-right:1px;
    padding-left:1px;
    mso-ignore:padding;
    color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:400;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:none;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;
    mso-number-format:General;
    text-align:left;
    vertical-align:top;
    mso-background-source:auto;
    mso-pattern:auto;
    white-space:normal;}
.xl694029
    {padding-top:1px;
    padding-right:1px;
    padding-left:1px;
    mso-ignore:padding;
    color:black;
    font-size:12.0pt;
    font-weight:400;
    font-style:normal;
    text-decoration:none;
    font-family:Garamond, serif;
    mso-font-charset:0;
    mso-number-format:General;
    text-align:left;
    vertical-align:top;
    border-top:none;
    border-right:none;
    border-bottom:none;
    border-left:.5pt solid windowtext;
    mso-background-source:auto;
    mso-pattern:auto;
    white-space:normal;}
--&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;Book1_4029&#34; align=center x:publishsource=&#34;Excel&#34;&gt;

&lt;table border=0 cellpadding=0 cellspacing=0 width=768 style=&#39;border-collapse:
 collapse;table-layout:fixed;width:576pt&#39;&gt;
 &lt;col class=xl654029 width=384 span=2 style=&#39;mso-width-source:userset;
 mso-width-alt:13653;width:288pt&#39;&gt;
 &lt;tr height=22 style=&#39;height:16.2pt&#39;&gt;
  &lt;td height=22 class=xl664029 width=384 style=&#39;height:16.2pt;width:288pt&#39;&gt;&lt;span
  style=&#39;mso-bidi-font-size:12pt&#39;&gt;Cost Distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=xl674029 width=384 style=&#39;width:288pt&#39;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-bidi-font-size:
  12pt&#39;&gt;Region Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
 &lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr height=445 style=&#39;mso-height-source:userset;height:333.6pt&#39;&gt;
  &lt;td height=445 class=xl684029 width=384 style=&#39;height:333.6pt;width:288pt&#39;&gt;1.
  Set the oceans to a one value source&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a. &lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;Use the
  Set null tool&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font
  class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Value&amp;quot; = 0, call the output “source.tif”&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font
  class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    2. Set all elevations in the DEM which are above the sea level rise
  threshold&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Set null tool again&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. &amp;quot;Value&amp;quot; &amp;gt; %Sea
  Level Rise% (in this case 2)&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;c. Set the false raster to 1 (Friction
  should be the same everywhere otherwise)&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;d. Call the output
  “friction.tif”&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;3. Create the cost distance surface&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Cost distance tool…&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Cost is “friction” source is
  “source”&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;c. Call the output distance&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;4. Remove the source cells to create a
  raster of just inundation&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Set null&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. “Value” = 0&lt;span
  style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;c. Again, set the value to 1
  otherwise&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;d. Call the output “SLRbyCost.tif”&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=xl694029 width=384 style=&#39;width:288pt&#39;&gt;1. Create a raster of all
  the areas less than the projected sea level rise.&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a. Hint:
  Use the set null tool to replace all values &amp;gt; sea level rise to null.&lt;span
  style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Otherwise, set the value to
  1&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;c. Call the output demlteslr&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;2. Group the resulting regions using region
  group&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Use 8 connectivity and group using the within method.&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Call the output regions&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;3. Use zonal statistics to identify the
  regions which contain an ocean source&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  We want the value of oceans (input value raster) using the regions as the
  zone data, and the maximum statistics.&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Call the output zonemax&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;4. We then want to remove the oceans from
  our calculation&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Hint: raster calculator (%zonemax%&amp;quot; - &amp;quot;%ocean%&amp;quot;).&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Call the output diff&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font54029&#34;&gt;5. Finally, sett everything less than or
  equal to 0 to null so that we have just the inundated pixels&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/font&gt;&lt;font class=&#34;font64029&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;a.
  Hint: Set null tool again&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;span style=&#39;mso-spacerun:yes&#39;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;b. Call the output SLRbyRegion&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
 &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer question 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-2-delineating-sea-level-rise-inundation-with-model-builder&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2: Delineating Sea Level Rise Inundation with Model Builder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ArcGIS we can use ModelBuilder to build a visual model that represents an analysis work flow. A ModelBuilder model typically consists of a set of data connected by a series of GIS operations. In this part we will be using ModelBuilder to create a model to delineate sea level rise inundation. Using a ModelBuilder model is helpful in situations where the model can be applied to numerous datasets, as we saw with the last lab.  Here you will use model builder to create both variants of the SLR workflow, one for Region Groups and one for Cost Distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-the-folders-for-the-lab&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up the folders for the lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In your lab 6 part 2 folder, create a new File Geodatabase.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R-Click &amp;gt; New &amp;gt; File Geodatabase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will be your new default workspace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add in the DEM and Ocean to the ArcMap, and examine them.  When done, remove them so you have a blank map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will also be helpful if you set overwrite to on

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geoprocessing &amp;gt; Geoprocessing Options &amp;gt; Overwrite the outputs…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-toolbox-and-a-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a Toolbox and a Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R-click on your lab 6 part 2 folder and create a &lt;strong&gt;new toolbox&lt;/strong&gt;. Name the new toolbox &lt;em&gt;InundationTools.tbx&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R-click on the toolbox and create a &lt;strong&gt;new model&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close the Model window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename the new Model (&lt;strong&gt;R-click | Rename&lt;/strong&gt;) to &lt;em&gt;InundationByRegionGroup&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-open the Model by R-clicking and selecting Edit…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up the Model Properties by going to &lt;strong&gt;Model | Model Properties&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the Environments tab, check the boxes for &lt;strong&gt;Processing Extent | Extent&lt;/strong&gt; and for &lt;strong&gt;Raster Analysis | Cell Size&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Values…&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the down arrows for each of the settings and make the &lt;strong&gt;Extent&lt;/strong&gt; the same as the &lt;em&gt;DEM&lt;/em&gt; raster in your data folder, and the &lt;strong&gt;Cell Size&lt;/strong&gt; the same as &lt;em&gt;DEM&lt;/em&gt; as well (they both have the same extent and cell size, if you check the data’s properties).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click OK on the Environment Settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click OK on the &lt;em&gt;InundationByRegionGroup&lt;/em&gt; Properties Window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-the-workflow-building-the-inundationbyregiongroup-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting up the Workflow &amp;amp; Building the InundationByRegionGroup Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will create a workflow diagram in the Model window that will show all the steps and operations/tools needed to delineate the sea level change. We start the process by dragging tools from ArcToolbox into the Model window to perform a specific operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open &lt;strong&gt;ArcToolbox&lt;/strong&gt; and set up your model window and ArcMap window so that you can see both ArcToolbox and the model window at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;Set Null&lt;/strong&gt; tool by finding it under ArcToolbox (Spatial Analyst Tools | Conditional) and then dragging it onto the model window.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before you set the options for the Set Null tool, create a &lt;strong&gt;Double variable from the Insert&lt;/strong&gt; menu. Rename it as ‘Sea Level Rise’, give the value of ‘2’ to the variable, and set it as a Model Parameter by checking Model Parameter option from its popup menu (right-click). The letter P appears beside the variable, indicating it is a model parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double click on the Set Null tool. The Set Null dialog will open, and it should be roughly similar to the dialog for Set Null in the spatial analyst.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the input conditional raster to DEM, and set the output to &lt;em&gt;demlteslr&lt;/em&gt; and make sure it is saved in the appropriate place. As for the expression, type in &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;Value&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt; %Sea Level Rise%&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click the input raster (DEM) and check Model Parameter option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To define input false raster or constant value, you need to create model variables for it. Right-click the Set Null. Click Make Variable &amp;gt; From Parameter &amp;gt; Input false layer or constant value. This adds the Input false layer or constant value as a variable in the model. Double-click it to assign ‘1’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You now have a simple model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right-click&lt;/strong&gt; the Set Null and select &lt;strong&gt;Run&lt;/strong&gt; to test your model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add, examine, and then remove the created Raster from the ArcMap window&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;strong&gt;Region Group tool&lt;/strong&gt; (Spatial Analyst Tools &amp;gt; Generalization) to your model.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;demlteslr&lt;/em&gt; as its input raster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;regions&lt;/em&gt; as an output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of neighboring cells to use is eight and use within for zone grouping method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncheck not to add link field to output and&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click OK to finish the Region Group dialog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right-click&lt;/strong&gt; the Region Group tool and select &lt;strong&gt;Run&lt;/strong&gt; to test your model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add examine, and then remove the created Raster from the ArcMap window&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a &lt;strong&gt;Zonal Statistics tool&lt;/strong&gt; (Spatial Analyst Tools &amp;gt; Zonal) to your model.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;regions&lt;/em&gt; as its input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;VALUE&lt;/em&gt; as a zone field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;em&gt;zonemax&lt;/em&gt; as an output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;Ocean&lt;/em&gt; as an input value raster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use maximum for statistics type, then click OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;em&gt;Ocean&lt;/em&gt; as a &lt;strong&gt;model parameter&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right-click&lt;/strong&gt; the Zonal Statistics and select &lt;strong&gt;Run&lt;/strong&gt; to test your model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add examine, and then remove the created Raster from the ArcMap window&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We now need to use the &lt;strong&gt;Raster Calculator&lt;/strong&gt; to calculate the difference between the &lt;em&gt;zonemax&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Ocean&lt;/em&gt;.

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: &lt;mark&gt;&lt;i&gt;(&amp;ldquo;%zonemax%&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;%Ocean%&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output as &lt;em&gt;diff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right-click&lt;/strong&gt; the Raster Calculator and select &lt;strong&gt;Run&lt;/strong&gt; to test your model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are going to add a &lt;strong&gt;Set Null&lt;/strong&gt; again to get our final output Inundation. Create another &lt;strong&gt;Double model variable&lt;/strong&gt;, to define the input false raster or constant value and give it a value ‘1.’ Set &lt;em&gt;diff&lt;/em&gt; as the tool’s input and type in the proper expression to query the values less and equal to zero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The final layout should look like so:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Right-click&lt;/strong&gt; the Set Null and select &lt;strong&gt;Run&lt;/strong&gt; to test your model.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saving-and-testing-your-whole-model&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saving and testing your whole model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click OK and Save your model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While you’re building your model, you can check if each tool (so far, we created 5 tools; Set Null, Set Null(2), Region Group, Zonal Statistics, and Raster Calculator for this model) you created works fine by right-clicking and running it (select Run). This time, let’s check if whole your model runs in one go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all tools are correctly established in the model, delete all of the output files (&lt;em&gt;delteslr, regions, zonemax, diff, inundation&lt;/em&gt;) from your output folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run your model using the appropriate inputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;now-recreate-the-cost-distance-approach&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now recreate the cost distance approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a new model using the cost distance approach to delineating sea level rise.  Your final model should look something like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer question 2-5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;part-3-sea-level-rise-inundation-delineation-with-python-scripting&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 3: Sea Level Rise Inundation Delineation with Python Scripting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part of the lab we will be using ArcGIS Python Command Window to do the same analysis we did in the first part. The main purpose is to show how such a model/analysis can be implemented by using a python script tool. We, therefore, will practice how to create ArcGIS Python tool using a python script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-script-tool&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a script tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within ArcGIS, you can create a script tool inside a toolbox. A script tool is like any other tool - it can be opened and executed from the tool dialog box, used in models and the &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt; window, and called from other scripts and script tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create a script tool, you need three things; a script, a custom toolbox, and a precise definition of the parameters of your script.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-custom-toolbox&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a custom toolbox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create your own toolbox called a custom toolbox and add tools and toolsets to it. Script and model tools that you create should be stored in a custom toolbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open ArcCatalog. In the Catalog Tree, navigate to the folder where you want the toolbox to be created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click the folder and click &lt;strong&gt;New &amp;gt; Toolbox&lt;/strong&gt;. Give the toolbox a new name &lt;em&gt;InundationToolbox.tbx&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create a script tool, right-click your custom toolbox and click &lt;strong&gt;Add &amp;gt; Script&lt;/strong&gt;. This opens the &lt;strong&gt;Add Script wizard&lt;/strong&gt; that takes you step by step through the process of creating a script tool. Give a new script a name &lt;em&gt;InundationByRegionGroupPython&lt;/em&gt; and add a script file by specifying the location of the file &lt;em&gt;InundationByRegionGroupPython.py&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image6.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the third step of the &lt;strong&gt;Add Script wizard&lt;/strong&gt;, add parameters by typing the name and selecting the data type as described in the table below. As for the property, use the default options unless specifically mentioned in the table below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Display Name&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Data Type&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Property&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Oceans&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Raster Dataset&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;DEM&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt;Raster Dataset&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td class=&#34;tg-btxf&#34;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Sea Level Rise&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Double&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Default: 2&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Inundation&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Raster Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th class=&#34;tg-0pky&#34;&gt;Direction: output&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;  

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After completing the steps, your toolbox will contain a new script tool. You can always modify properties (such as parameter names and data types) of this script tool by right-clicking the script tool and choosing &lt;strong&gt;Properties&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double click the script file you just added. The &lt;em&gt;InundationByRegionGroupPython&lt;/em&gt; tool dialog will appear and it should look like this image below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog558/media/Lab6Image7.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input &lt;em&gt;ocean&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;dem&lt;/em&gt; for the first two input layers. Use the default value for Sea Level Rise. Save &lt;em&gt;Inundation&lt;/em&gt; in your part02 folder as an output layer. Click OK to run the tool. Answer question 6-9.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When finished, submit your work to blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
