<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Courses | Jim Coll</title>
    <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Courses</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog358/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/geog358/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;welcome-to-geog358-introduction-to-gis&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome to GEOG358: Introduction to GIS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Note: This is a living document.  Changes will be announced in class.  A pdf version of this page is available for download &lt;a href=&#34;urlhere&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-description&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Description:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course provides an introduction to computer based analysis of spatial data.  Topics covered include the fundamentals of geospatial thought, basic principles of collecting, storing, analyzing, and displaying spatial data, and cursory treatment of analysis and decision making.  Emphasis is on problem solving activities using common spatial analytical techniques using typical applications as examples. The student will gain extensive hands on experience with state of the art GIS software in the lab. This course introduces the concepts and components of a geographic information system (GIS). It also teaches the essential skills of operating a functional GIS through the use of the ArcGIS software suite. By completing this course, students will understand the operational processes of spatial data acquisition, editing in ArcGIS Desktop with QA/QC, metadata development, geodatabase design, spatial query and display, spatial analysis and modeling, preliminary GIS application development, cartographic mapping and dynamic visualization, and GIS implementation basics. Students will also be exposed to Google Earth and common Free and  Open Source Software (FOSS) tools, as well as the basic concepts of remote sensing and Global Positioning System (GPS). GIS technology has broad applications in natural and social sciences, humanities, environmental studies, engineering, and management. Examples include wildlife habitat study, urban and regional planning, contagious disease monitoring, agriculture and forestry, environmental quality assessment, emergency management, transportation planning, consumer and competitor analysis, and many more. This course will introduce a few selected use cases of GIS application in different disciplines.  Finally, this class counts towards the &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalog.ku.edu/liberal-arts-sciences/geography/geographic-information-science-ucert/&#34;&gt;Undergraduate certificate in GIS&lt;/a&gt;.  I obviously recommend it, particularly if you intend to pursue GIS as a career path/toolset in any capacity .&lt;br/&gt;
Satisfies: Lab and Field Experiences (LFE), Natural Science (N)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;student-responsibilities&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Responsibilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is student’s responsibility to attend the lectures, do the readings, and finish lab assignments. All students should be prepared to participate in class discussion and answer questions when called upon.  All students are expected to complete labs and exams on time. Labs are due at the beginning of the lab period one week after they are assigned, unless otherwise noted. Detailed lab rules will be given by the teaching assistant in the first lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;expectations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expectations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attend every Class/lab and &lt;strong&gt;ask questions!&lt;/strong&gt; At times, the ArcGIS software can be very unforgiving, and GIS can seem like a foreign language. The last thing I want is for you to walk out of this class without understanding the material. I expect and hope that this will be a rewarding experience for everyone. We are available to answer questions and otherwise offer assistance during the office hours indicated above or by appointment.  Additionally, if you have any questions, feel free to drop me an e-mail or use the slack channel (The link will be passed around on the signup sheet at the beginning of the year). I try to be diligent about responding to emails and by using slack you are likely to get a very rapid response&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computers in the lab are not cheap to replace. Please do your part to lengthen their lives by not spilling coffee/soda/liquids of any kind on the computer or any of its parts. You do NOT need to go out and purchase a computer for this class, although I do recommend having a personal computer with ArcGIS installed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computer recommendations:  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
ArcGIS is a demanding program, and a lower grade computer is not recommended.  If you are at KU, IT offers &lt;a href=&#34;https://kuit.service-now.com/kb_view.do?sysparm_article=KB0011590&#34;&gt;virtualLabs&lt;/a&gt;, a remote desktop program you can use to access ArcMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to purchase a computer, I offer these general guidelines. You should aim for a 64-bit computer (x64), and aside from that I like to prioritize CPU &amp;amp; RAM &amp;gt; video &amp;amp; hard drive speed &amp;gt; hard drive space (External hard drives are really cheap, and as long as the computer has a USB port you are good to go).  A few specific recommendations I found last year with a quick Google:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lenovo Miix 510 &amp;amp; Dell Inspiron 15 7000​: Decent budget computers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acer Aspire V15​ &amp;amp; Dell Inspiron i7: Slightly higher end machines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I tend to stay away from the &amp;ldquo;gaming&amp;rdquo; laptops.  For those prices, you can build a much more powerful desktop and get a lot more mileage out of it, but that&amp;rsquo;s just me.  If you want to go that route however virtually all will meet your school related needs.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pcpartpicker.com/user/JColl/saved/#view=zddq3C&#34;&gt;My “Ideal” build (This is excessive, visualization grade)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lab is open for students whenever there is no scheduled class (see the calendar posted on the lab door. Additionally, ArcMap is available in the GIS lab on the second floor of Watson Library, and on the Architecture and Engineering computers if you have access to those. A signup sheet will also be passed around at the beginning of the semester for those who wish to install ArcGIS on your own personal computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-integrity&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academic Integrity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, cheating and/or plagiarism &lt;strong&gt;is not tolerated&lt;/strong&gt;. Feel free to discuss the labs with your classmates, but all work you turn in should be your own, and it&amp;rsquo;s insert year here, how hard is it to give someone credit for their work?  As a graduate student, I became increadably familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; for my citation needs, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.citethisforme.com/us/citation-generator&#34;&gt;Cite This for Me&lt;/a&gt; will also work for you in a pinch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disabilities&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disabilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has a disability that may prevent full demonstration of academic ability should contact me as soon as possible to ensure accommodations can be made to allow for full educational benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-labs&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the Labs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a cartography course; however, the final product of the majority of the labs is a map (or maps) of some sort. The grade you receive on the maps will be based primarily on the results of the relevant analysis, not cartographic technique (there is a whole class dedicated to this; GEOG 211). That said, some level of cartographic knowledge will be useful to effectively communicate with maps, and will be stressed in critiques of your submissions. As the semester wears on we expect improvements and may begin taking points off for excessively bad cartographic technique. Please refer to the cartography resources linked below for some basic guidelines or ask for feedback.  In addition, each lab will specify the steps to follow with regards to what to submit for grading and how to do so. Please don’t make assumptions. Follow these instructions carefully; failure to submit the correct files or submission of files in an incorrect fashion will result in drastic loss of points. Don’t turn a potential A into an F due to failure to follow directions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cartography-primers&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cartography primers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&#34;&gt;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&#34;&gt;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://colorbrewer2.org/#type=sequential&amp;amp;scheme=BuGn&amp;amp;n=3&#34;&gt;http://colorbrewer2.org/#type=sequential&amp;amp;scheme=BuGn&amp;amp;n=3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;textbooks&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbooks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;de Smith, M. J., M. F. Goodchild, P. A. Longley (2012) &lt;em&gt;Geospatial Analysis—A comprehensive guide&lt;/em&gt; (4&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; edition), An online version is available at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&#34;&gt;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-evaluation&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Evaluation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course grade will be evaluated based on two exams, pre-class review questions, ~ten lab exercises, and a final project. The exams will include materials from the textbooks, lecture slides, handouts, and labs. A breakdown of grade weights is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exam 17.5%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-class review 5%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labs 40%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Final Project 20%&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade will be on a straight scale, not on a curve. If you all do well, you will all get an A. Let’s not find out what the alternative is. Letter grades will be determined based on the standard grading scale. Each student will complete a final project. The project will be presented to the class during the last two weeks of class. Details on the final project can be found in the final project handout. Letter grades will be determined based on the following grading scale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;D-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;F&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;100 - 97&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;96 - 93&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;92 - 90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;89 - 87&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;86 - 83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;82 - 80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;79 - 77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;76 - 73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;72 - 70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;69 - 67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;66 - 63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;62 - 60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exams&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mid-term exam will cover the materials from the first half of the class, and the final exam will focus on the second half. The final exam is not comprehensive, but since we will be building on concepts throughout the semester, materials from the first half of the semester will inevitably be part of the final exam.  Either exam may include a practical portion.  This practical portion will consist of instructions to prepare some sort of short analysis or demonstration of practical knowledge related to the use of ArcGIS.  These will be posted either a week before the exam and due on the date of the exam, or posted the day of the exam and due a week after.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/YUN00120.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;drones-for-mapping-and-research&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drones for mapping and research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting aspects of working in the Environmental Sciences is in exploring how the application of new tools and technologies has allowed us to reimagine and streamline how we observe, process, understand, and communicate the state of the world.  Take for instance, the humble terrain surface.  Although I’m not quite old enough to recall walking to school uphill both ways in a snowstorm, there was once a time when the USGS topo maps were the gold standard in terms of how closely we could replicate the undulations of landforms, and can recall many a boy scout meeting where we used these maps to plan our next adventure.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/KS_Lawrence West.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 2000, we brought these representations to the digital domain with the flight of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/srtm/mission.htm&#34;&gt;Shuttle Radar Topography Mission.&lt;/a&gt;  This gave us a digital representation of the world at a ~25-meter resolution across much of the globe.  Fantastic for most large-scale representations, this is still entirely too large to be relevant at a building scale.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/GISData.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next major milestone wouldn’t be seen until early 2016 with the USGS announcement of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usgs.gov/core-science-systems/ngp/3dep&#34;&gt;3D Elevation Program (3DEP)&lt;/a&gt;.  This program set standards for the collection and curation of Airborne LIDAR (Light Detection and Ranging).  These data are high resolution point representations of elevation, with an average spacing of &amp;gt;4 points per square meter with less than 6 cm of variation across a flat surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/FY19_Partnerships_territories_08212019.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
This represents a major leap forward but is not without its drawbacks.  Firstly, although LIDAR collects elevations, it does not collect imagery, which makes viewing the surface much less intuitive than it would otherwise be.  Additionally, although the resulting elevations are accurate, they are still not dense enough or accurate enough to compete with high precision surveys, and depending on the use case, may be out of date by more than 3 years.  In these instances, small Unmanned Aerial Systems, more commonly known as drones, offer a unique solution to some of these shortcomings.  Using commercially available hardware and cutting-edge software, we are able to fly over an area and collect imagery which we use to create our own custom point clouds and 3D models.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/OreadOrthoTrimmedSmaller.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://jimcoll.github.io/courses/dronemapping/YUN00016.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
As a critical part of my dissertation, I am interested in flying areas to determine what factors go into an effective terrestrial mapping effort.  The above images are a small sampling of outputs which I can generate, but can also include 3D point clouds, photorealistic models, updated aerial maps, and standard aerial photography outputs.  If you have an area you would like flown, particularly if it has interesting and complex geometry or if it’s near a body of water, please contact me at jcoll AT ku.edu and we’ll find a way to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ku-natural-history-museum-s-science-on-tap&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KU Natural History Museum’s Science on Tap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small presentation for KU Natural History Museum’s Science on Tap | Free State Brewing CO.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
