<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Courses | Jim Coll</title>
    <link>https://JimColl.github.io/courses/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://JimColl.github.io/courses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Courses</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://JimColl.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Courses</title>
      <link>https://JimColl.github.io/courses/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>https://JimColl.github.io/courses/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://JimColl.github.io/courses/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;#&lt;strong&gt;Welcome to GEOG358: Introduction to GIS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Description:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course teaches An introduction to computer based analysis of spatial data.  Topics
covered include the fundamentals of geospatial thought, basic
principles of collecting, storing, analyzing, and displaying spatial
data, and cursory analysis and decision making. Emphasis is on problem solving activities using common spatial
analytical techniques (e.g., map overlay). The student will gain
extensive hands  on experience with state of the art GIS software in the
lab. This course introduces the concepts and components of a geographic
information system (GIS). It also teaches the essential skills of
operating a functional GIS through the use of the ArcGIS software suite.
By completing this course, students will understand the operational
processes of spatial data acquisition, editing in ArcGIS Desktop with
QA/QC, metadata development, geodatabase design, spatial query and
display, spatial analysis and modeling, preliminary GIS application
development, cartographic mapping and dynamic visualization, and GIS
implementation basics. Students will also be exposed to Google Earth and
common Free and  Open Source Software (FOSS) tools, as well as the basic concepts of remote
sensing and Global Positioning System (GPS). GIS technology has broad
applications in natural and social sciences, humanities, environmental
studies, engineering, and management. Examples include wildlife habitat
study, urban and regional planning, contagious disease monitoring,
agriculture and forestry, environmental quality assessment, emergency
management, transportation planning, consumer and competitor analysis,
and many more. This course will introduce a few selected use cases of GIS
application in different disciplines.
Satisfies: Lab and Field
Experiences (LFE), N Natural Science (N)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Responsibilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is student’s responsibility to attend the lectures, do the readings,
and finish lab assignments. All students should be prepared to
participate in class discussion and answer questions when called upon.
All students are expected to complete labs and exams on time. Labs are
due at the beginning of the lab period one week after they are assigned,
unless otherwise noted. Detailed lab rules will be given by the teaching
assistant in the first lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expectations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attend every Class/lab and &lt;span class=&#34;underline&#34;&gt;ask
questions!&lt;/span&gt; At times, the ArcGIS software can be very
unforgiving, and GIS can seem like a foreign language. The last thing I
want is for you to walk out of this class without understanding the
material. I expect and hope that this will be a rewarding experience for
everyone. We are available to answer questions and otherwise offer
assistance during the office hours indicated above or by appointment.
Additionally, if you have any questions, feel free to drop me an e-mail
or use the slack channel (The link will be passed around on the signup
sheet at the beginning of the year). I try to be diligent about
responding to emails and by using slack you are likely to get a very
rapid response&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computers in the lab are not cheap to replace. Please do your part
to lengthen their lives by not spilling coffee/soda/liquids of any kind
on the computer or any of its parts. You do NOT need to go out and
purchase a computer for this class, although I do recommend having a
personal computer with ArcGIS installed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computer recommendations:  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to purchase a computer, I offer these general
guidelines. You should aim for a 64-bit computer (x64), and aside from
that I like to prioritize CPU &amp;amp; RAM &amp;gt; video &amp;amp; hard drive speed &amp;gt; hard
drive space (External hard drives are really cheap, and as long as the
computer has a USB port you are good to go).  A few specific
recommendations I found last year with a quick google:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lenovo Miix 510 &amp;amp; Dell Inspiron 15 7000​: Decent budget computers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Acer Aspire V15​ &amp;amp; Dell Inspiron i7: Slightly higher end machines&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, I tend to stay away from the &amp;ldquo;gaming&amp;rdquo; laptops.  For those
prices, you can build a much more powerful desktop and get a lot more
mileage out of it, but that&amp;rsquo;s just me.  If you want to go that route
virtually all will meet your school related needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My “Ideal” build (This is excessive, research grade):
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pcpartpicker.com/user/JColl/saved/#view=zddq3C&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://pcpartpicker.com/user/JColl/saved/#view=zddq3C&lt;/a&gt;​&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lab is open for students whenever there is no scheduled class (see
the calendar posted on the lab door. Additionally, ArcMap is available
in the GIS lab on the second floor of Watson Library, and on the
Architecture and Engineering computers if you have access to those. A
signup sheet will also be passed around at the beginning of the semester
for those who wish to install ArcGIS on your own personal computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Academic Integrity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, cheating and/or plagiarism &lt;span class=&#34;underline&#34;&gt;is not
tolerated&lt;/span&gt;. Feel free to discuss the labs with your classmates,
but all work you turn in should be your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disabilities:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has a disability that may prevent full demonstration of
academic ability should contact me as soon as possible to ensure
accommodations can be made to allow for full educational benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About the Labs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a cartography course; however, the final product of the
majority of the labs is a map (or maps) of some sort. The grade you
receive on the maps will be based primarily on the results of the
relevant analysis, not cartographic technique (there is a whole class
dedicated to this; GEOG 211). That said, some level of cartographic
knowledge will be useful to effectively communicate with maps, and will
be stressed in critiques of your submissions. As the semester wears on
we expect improvements and may begin taking points off for excessively
bad cartographic technique. Please refer to the cartography resources
linked below for some basic guidelines or ask for feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, each lab will specify the steps to follow with regards to
what to submit for grading and how to do so. Please don’t make
assumptions. Follow these instructions carefully; failure to submit the
correct files or submission of files in an incorrect fashion will result
in drastic loss of points. Don’t turn a potential A into an F due to
failure to follow directions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cartography primers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.icsm.gov.au/mapping/cartographic.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://frew.eri.ucsb.edu/private/ESM263/week/2/ESM-263-2017-02-Cartography_Basics.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textbooks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;de Smith, M. J., M. F. Goodchild, P. A. Longley (2012) &lt;em&gt;Geospatial
Analysis—A comprehensive guide&lt;/em&gt; (4&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; edition), An online
version is available at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.spatialanalysisonline.com/HTML/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tentative Course Outline:&lt;/strong&gt;
| &lt;strong&gt;Week number&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt; | &lt;strong&gt;Milestones&lt;/strong&gt;                     | &lt;strong&gt;Class&lt;/strong&gt;                       | &lt;strong&gt;Lab&lt;/strong&gt;                | &lt;strong&gt;Due&lt;/strong&gt;              |
|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;:|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;:|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-:|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-:|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-:|:&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;:|
| Week 1          | 27-Aug  | Welcomes                           | Walk through                    |                        |                      |
|                 | 29-Aug  | Last day for a full refund &lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt;    | ESRI UC                         |                        |                      |
| Week 2          | 3-Sep   |                                    | Coordinate systems, projections | Introduction to ArcMap | Week 1 review        |
|                 | 5-Sep   |                                    | Data Models and structures      |                        |                      |
| Week 3          | 10-Sep  |                                    | GIS Data                        | Datum Shift lab        | Week 2 review        |
|                 | 12-Sep  | Last day to drop without a w &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;16&lt;/sub&gt;  | GPS                             |                        |                      |
| Week 4          | 17-Sep  |                                    | Getting Data                    | GPS lab                | Week 3 review        |
|                 | 19-Sep  | Last day to add or swap class &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;23&lt;/sub&gt; | Map Design                      |                        |                      |
| Week 5          | 24-Sep  |                                    | Map Design                      | Building A database    | Week 4 review        |
|                 | 26-Sep  |                                    | Map Design                      |                        |                      |
| Week 6          | 1-Oct   |                                    | Vector Data Analysis            | Overlay lab            | Week 5 review        |
|                 | 3-Oct   |                                    | Overlay analysis                |                        |                      |
| Week 7          | 8-Oct   |                                    | Midterm Review                  | No Lab                 | Week 6 review        |
|                 | 10-Oct  |                                    | Midterm                         |                        | Project proposal due |
| Week 8          | 15-Oct  | Fall Break!                       | No Class                        | Spatial Statistics Lab |                      |
|                 | 17-Oct  |                                    | Spatial Statistics              |                        |                      |
| Week 9          | 22-Oct  |                                    | Spatial Statistics              | Interpolation Lab      |                      |
|                 | 24-Oct  |                                    | Raster Data Analysis            |                        |                      |
| Week 10         | 29-Oct  |                                    | Network Analysis                | Network Analysis       | Week 8-9 review     |
|                 | 31-Oct  |                                    | Guest Lecture                   |                        |                      |
| Week 11         | 5-Nov   |                                    | Terrain Analysis                | Hydrology Lab          | week 10 review       |
|                 | 7-Nov   |                                    | Terrain Analysis                |                        |                      |
| Week 13         | 12-Nov  |                                    | Guest Lecture                   | Distribution  modeling | weel 11 review       |
|                 | 14-Nov  |                                    | Make up day                     |                        |                      |
| Week 14         | 19-Nov  | Las day to withdraw                | Make up day                     | Open Lab               |                      |
|                 | 21-Nov  |                                    | Project Help                    |                        |                      |
| Week 15         | 26-Nov  |                                    | Project Help                    | Open Lab               | Introduction due     |
|                 | 28-Nov  | ThxGiving Break!                  | No Class                        |                        |                      |
| Week 16         | 3-Dec   |                                    | Final Project presentations     | No Lab                 |                      |
|                 | 5-Dec   |                                    | Final Project presentations     |                        |                      |
| Week 17         | 10-Dec  | AGU - no class                    | Practical Final on your own     | No Lab                 |                      |
|                 | 12-Dec  | AGU - no class                    | Practical Final on your own     |                        |                      |
| Week 18         | 17-Dec  | Final                              | Final at 1:30                   |                        | Final Paper Due      |&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other “important” dates:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://registrar.ku.edu/fall-2019-academic-calendar-date&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://registrar.ku.edu/fall-2019-academic-calendar-date&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Evaluation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Course grade will be evaluated based on two exams, pre-class review questions, ~ten lab exercises,
and a final project. The exams will include materials from the
textbooks, lecture slides, handouts, and labs. Mid-term exam will cover
the materials from the first half of the class, and the final exam will
focus on the second half. The final exam is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; comprehensive, but
since we will be building on concepts throughout the semester, materials
from the first half of the semester will inevitably be part of the final
exam. A breakdown of grade weights is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Midterm exam 15%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final exam 15%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pre-class review 15%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Labs 40%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final Project 20%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade will be on a straight scale, not on a curve. If you all do
well, you will all get an A. Let’s not find out what the alternative is.
Letter grades will be determined based on the standard grading scale.
Each student will complete a final project. The project will be
presented to the class during the last two weeks of class. Details on
the final project can be found in the final project handout. Letter
grades will be determined based on the following grading scale:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;A-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;B-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;C-&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;F&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;93-100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90-92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87-89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;83-86&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80-82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;77-79&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73-76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70-72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60-69&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&amp;lt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GEOG358 Final Project and Term Paper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identify a biophysical, human, or environmental problem that requires
spatial analysis using GIS. Describe the problem that you are interested
in. Discuss what kind of GIS analysis you want to use and the
implementation strategy you have chosen. Present simple diagrams or maps
that illustrate your approach. Apply your approach to real-world data
and present the results of your project in oral form. &lt;strong&gt;All students&lt;/strong&gt;
are also required to write a term paper based on the final project. The
intermediate deliverables count towards 10% of the final project grade,
the term paper counts 65% of the final project grade and the
presentation counts towards the remaining 25%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All students are required to write a proposal for the final project. In
the proposal, you will describe the project you are planning to carry
out, the GIS datasets needed, and GIS analysis functions may be used in
the project. You will review the literature (especially for graduate
students) what methods and GIS analysis functions have been used solving
similar problems. Each student should plan on a 15-minutes presentation
of your final project to the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term paper should include the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the problem in context. Describe why spatial analysis is
needed to solve your problem. Review in literature what methods
and spatial analysis have been used solving similar problems. Be
sure to include a statement like &amp;ldquo;The objective of this project
is to &amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methods&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Describe the strategy you solve the problem using GIS and any
other necessary methods. Describe the statistic method, computer
model, GIS analytic functions / operations you use in the
problem solving process. Diagrams are especial helpful to
understand your strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Study Area and Analysis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Describe the study area. What kind of GIS data and data models
are used in the analysis. Present the results of your analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Results &amp;amp; Conclusions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss the findings from your problem solving process. Evaluate
your methodology. Discuss the usefulness and limitation of the
analytic functions in GIS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are due throughout the semester:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposal&lt;/strong&gt; (1 ~ 3 pages, due tentatively on &lt;strong&gt;Oct 10&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt; (due &lt;strong&gt;Nov. 26&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full Term Paper&lt;/strong&gt; (6 ~ 15 pages, due on &lt;strong&gt;Dec 17&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
